<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking glasse of mortalitie. Not verie pleasant at the first view to many men, but yet most necessarie, profitable and commodious for all sorts of people, of what estate dignity, or calling soeuer they be. : With an Exhortation to good life annexed: wherein are treated all such things as appertaine vnto a Christian to do, from the beginning of his conuersion, vntill the end of his perfection. / Made by I.B..</title>
            <author>I. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1041.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124171</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">54532265</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 54532265</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180713</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00023)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180713)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2125:14a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking glasse of mortalitie. Not verie pleasant at the first view to many men, but yet most necessarie, profitable and commodious for all sorts of people, of what estate dignity, or calling soeuer they be. : With an Exhortation to good life annexed: wherein are treated all such things as appertaine vnto a Christian to do, from the beginning of his conuersion, vntill the end of his perfection. / Made by I.B..</title>
                  <author>I. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by R. F. for Iohn Oxenbridge, dwelling at the signe of the Parrat in Paules churchyard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G¹².</note>
                  <note>Printers' device on G₁₁v (McK. 288); headpiece, initials.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Bound and filmed preceding STC (2nd ed.) 6832.65 "A dyet for the Christian soule".</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: C1 and G12, (the last probably blank) lacking; tightly bound and stained, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:4"/>
            <p>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>OOKING GLASSE of Mortalitie.</p>
            <p>Not verie pleaſant at the firſt view to many men, but yet moſt neceſſarie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and commodious for all ſorts of people of what eſtate, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity, or calling ſoeuer they be.</p>
            <p>With an Exhortation to good life annexed: Wherein are treated all ſuch things at appertaine vnto a Chriſtian to do, from the beginning of his conuerſion, vntill the end of his perfection.</p>
            <p>Made by I. B.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by R. F. for Iohn Oxenbridge, dwelling at the ſigne of the Parrat in <hi>Paules churchyard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:5"/>
            <head>DEATH TO THE careleſſe youth.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>YOu careleſſe youth looke well on me,</l>
               <l>For as I am, ſo ſhall you be:</l>
               <l>I am the wight, at length that muſt</l>
               <l>Lay all your glorie in the duſt:</l>
               <l>Tis I, tis I, that giues the fall</l>
               <l>To eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie one, though neere ſo tall:</l>
               <l>No wealth, no ſtrength, nor pollicie</l>
               <l>Can make reſiſtance vnto me.</l>
               <l>Wherefore let this be ſtill your ſong,</l>
               <l>Dead ſhall I be, ere it be long.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Death to the gallant dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Dames.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YE gallant Dames, behold your doome,</l>
                  <l>To this at length you all muſt come:</l>
                  <l>Though neere ſo fine, you are but duſt,</l>
                  <l>Though neere ſo loath, away you muſt:</l>
                  <l>I daunt your pride, I pull your plumes,</l>
                  <l>To ſtench I turne, your ſweet perfumes:</l>
                  <l>Your Rings, your Chaines, your rich aray,</l>
                  <l>Yea life and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> take away.</l>
                  <l>Let this therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>cke your ſong,</l>
                  <l>Dead ſhall I be, ere it be long.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:6"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOR TO the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Let euerie man, if he be wife,</l>
               <l>Though he be not exprest by name.</l>
               <l>With indgement deep, and good aduiſe,</l>
               <l>Mark wel this Glaſſe: for in the ſame</l>
               <l>A perfect picture painted is,</l>
               <l>Of euerlaſting bale or blis.</l>
               <l>Moſt ſure we are, that we muſt die,</l>
               <l>But when, or how, God only knowes:</l>
               <l>O ten times happie then, ſay I,</l>
               <l>Is he that well his time beſt owes:</l>
               <l>But wo to him ten thouſand fold,</l>
               <l>Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death as priſoner faſt doth hold.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180713:6"/>
            <head>A LOOKING GLASSE OF MORTALITIE.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That of neceſſitie all men muſt die.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat we muſt all once die, there is no Athieſt ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous, nor no foole ſo ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 9.5.</note> but doth know and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the ſame; being compelled thereunto, not only by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the holy Scriptures and learned Fathers, but alſo by dayly and howerly experience.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180713:7"/>The ſentence is giuen, which cannot be recalled:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>n.</hi> 3.19.</note> duſt we are &amp; into duſt we muſt needs returne againe, we all muſt die, and ſinke into the ground like waters, which returneth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 145.</note> Man that is borne of a woman, faith <hi>Iob,</hi> hath, but a ſhort time to line, and that litle time alſo that he hath is reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with manifold miſeries, his daies be ſhort,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>el.</hi> 17.3.</note> &amp; the hower of death is vncertaine, the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of his moneths are ſet downe which hee cannot paſſe, but when they are complete, there is no remedy but die he muſt: <hi>Quis eſt homo qui viuit &amp; non videbit mortem:</hi> What man is he that liueth and ſhall not die? ſurely not one, for al fleſh is but Graſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 88.49. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 40.</note> and all our glory but as the Flowers of the field, which to day flouriſh and to morrow
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180713:7"/>wither and are caſt into the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> when Death commeth with his Siclein hand to haue in his harueſt, he looketh not on the greene and flouriſhing yeares of young <hi>Ganimedes,</hi> he regardeth not the Purple robes of Senatours, nor paſſeth not a ſtraw for <hi>Creſus</hi> yellow crownes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 88.</note> he feareth not the force of <hi>Mars,</hi> nor ſubtility of <hi>Mercurie:</hi> neither <hi>Caeſar,</hi> nor <hi>Alexander,</hi> could reſiſt him, neither <hi>Salomon</hi> nor <hi>V liſſes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile him. <hi>Neque ſalunb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium,</hi> neither ſhall the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the wicked helpe him, but downe he muſt amongſt the reſt: Graſſe we are,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and as Graſſe will he mow vs, all haue ſinned, and for ſin we all muſt die. It is decreed that all muſt once die, but woe to him that dieth twiſe, the firſt death par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180713:8"/>ſoule and body,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 9. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ors</hi> 2.</note> the ſecond death ſeperateth both body &amp; ſoule from God, the firſt depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs of temporall pleaſures,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>poc.</hi> 2.</note> the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bereaueth vs of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioyes.</p>
               <p>Well may we all ſtand in feare of death: for in what ſtate he findeth vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ug. in Epiſt</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> in that eſtate ſhall we be preſented before the tribunall ſeate of God: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we when we depart cary any thing with vs but our good deeds and our bad; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked came we into the world,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; naked muſt we depart again, &amp; when we are dead, there is no difference at all betweene one Carkaſſe and another,<note place="margin">Amb. inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> vnleſſe perchaunce the rich mans Corſe ſtinke more vilely then the poore mans doth, neither doth it make much to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whether we haue liued te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180713:8"/>ten hundred yeares, for when our glaſſe is run out, and ineui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table death is come, all is one in effect,<note place="margin">Hiero. ad Heliodor.</note> but that he that hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued longeſt, ſhall haue the greater burthen of ſin to beare and the more to account for: much better is it to liué a little while and vertuouſly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sene.</hi> 79. <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
                  </note> then a thouſand yeres wickedly: bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is one day to a wiſe and learned man, then a very long life to him that liueth lewdly and followeth his ſenſualities.</p>
               <p>But what make I ſo much a do, to proue ſo plaine a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by ſo many authorities of ſacred Scriptures and holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? the very heathens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that knew not God, do in their writings confeſſe the ſame;<note place="margin">Plato.</note> aske <hi>Plato</hi> what he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of this life, and he will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere you, <hi>Sapientum vita me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatio
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180713:9"/>eſt mortis,</hi> that is, the life of wiſe men ought to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall meditation of death, which will come, nothing more ſure, but when and how, no man cant tell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seneca Ep.</hi> 72.</note> aske <hi>Seneca</hi> his iudgement herein, and he will not only confirme that I haue ſayd, but proue it by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Certum eſt</hi> (faith he) <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam mortémque per vices ire &amp; compoſit a diſſolui, &amp; diſſolut a componi, omne humanum genus quodcunque eſt, quodcunque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit morte damnatum est, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ius.</note> It is certaine, that life and death come and go by turnes: things made and compounded are to be diſſolued, and being diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued are to be made againe. All generations of men whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer are or ſhall be condemned to die, and the Cities that now are builded ſhall one day de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180713:9"/>and men ſhall aske, where ſtood ſuch a towne? And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seneca.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Morior nec primus nec vltimus, omnes me anteceſſerunt, omnes ſequente hac conditione intraui, vt exirem.</hi> All thoſe that liued before me, are dead &amp; gone before me, and all that are to come ſhall follow me. I came into the world vpon that condition,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seneca.</hi> 24. <hi>Ep.</hi>
                  </note> that I ſhould depart againe: And as long as I liue I dayly die, for ſome part of my time doth daly ſhorten, and as my yeares increaſe, ſo doth my life decreaſe, our Infancie, our childhood, and all our youth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto yeſterday is loſt, all our time paſſed is periſhed, &amp; euen this very day we dined with death. And as olde age commeth after youth, ſo death followeth old age. Yet would I not wiſh thee to liue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180713:10"/>in hope of long life,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seneca.</hi> 1. <hi>Epi.</hi>
                  </note> for thou knoweſt not in what corner death doth lie in waite for thee: and ſeeing thou knoweſt not where he lurketh, it were good for thee to expect him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery hower, and ſuſpect him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where. And if death be to be feared,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seneca Epi.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> he is alwayes to be feared: for what hower is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from death? yet to the end thou maiſt not feare death, be thou alwayes mindfull of him: Thus farre <hi>Seneca.</hi> who though he were a heathen, may ſet vs all to ſchoole. O key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cold Catholike! ô negligent Chriſtian! how canſt thou heare this without bluſhing? how art thou not confounded to thinke hereupon? Shall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels that know nor God, teach thee to liue like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian? ſhall heathe as that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180713:10"/>hoped for heauen or fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hell, teach vs how to liue &amp; die well? what can we ſay to this? ſurely I feare me much, that as they are our ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſters now in this point, ſo ſhall they be our accuſers and iudges at the latter day: they expected no reward after this life, yet dayly indeuored to liue and die well, and we that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that there is a moſt iuſt and vpright Iudge, that ſhall reward the good with euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glorie, and the bad with perpetuall paines, neuer or very ſeldome thinke on death, but liue as if there were no ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>matter.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heu vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>t homines tanquans mors nullu ſequatur,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et velut Infernum fabula vana for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:180713:11"/>
                     <l>Men liue and yet beleeue not, that death ſhall ouer take them:</l>
                     <l>The paines of hell they feare not, But fables they do make them.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What great commoditie commeth vnto man by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall meditation and memorie of death.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MEmento homo quia puluis es in puluerem reuerte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> Remember ô man that thou art but duſt, and into duſt ſhalt thou returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, nothing ſo much daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the pride of man, as the remembraunce of his baſe beginning, and miſerable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. If we remember what we were in our mothers wombe, we cannot but bluſh for ſhame, If we conſider what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180713:11"/>we are now, we ſhall find ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cauſes to weepe &amp; lament, and if we die, way well what we ſhall ſhortly be, we ſhould both tremble and quake for feare: Our beginning was ſuch as with honeſtie it cannot be named, our preſent ſtate ſo full of miſeries as no man can num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, and our paſſage out of this life ſo painefull and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous, as no tongue can tell or pen expreſſe the ſame: men would thinke hereupon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> O that and prudently foreſee &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for this dreadfull hower. Ah God, how many thouſand ſoules lie now broiling and burning in hell, curſing &amp; ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that euer they were borne, and all for want of theſe conſiderations, which had they remembred, they might perhaps haue bin happie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180713:12"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oules and glorious Saints in heauen.</p>
               <p>The memory of death is a moſt precious preſeruatiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all peſtilent deſeaſes of the ſoule, and a preſent reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for all ſickneſſe of ſin what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. The memory of death is the mother of humilitie, the nurſe of all vertues, the bane of pride, and ſtep dame of al vices. The memory of death purgeth all miſdemeanour, diſſolute and light behauiour, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth vs from all hainous crimes and enormities whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. <hi>Memor are nouiſſima tua</hi> (faith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>&amp; in aeternum non peccabis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.</note> Remember thy laſt things, and thou ſhalt neuer ſinne. As for example, who could take pride to behold him ſelfe in a Glaſſe, or to looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his ſtraite and well ſet
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180713:12"/>legges, or to heare himſelfe commended for his comlineſſe of perſon, if hee remembred that:<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> 
                  <hi>Adhuc puſillum &amp; non erit peccatum, ſed in modica foſſa computreſoenti &amp; oſſa.</hi> After a little while ſinfull man muſt die, and then he ſhall be put into a little hole of the ground, where both fleſh and bones ſhall rot and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to nothing. Or who would be delighted to heare himſelfe prattle, or glorie in his ready and pregnant wit, if he did bethinke him, that <hi>Poſt hominem vermes, poſt vermem foetor, ſic in non hominem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur omnis homo.</hi> Shortly, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to morrow, perhaps to day his tongue ſhall falter, his voyce decay, his memory faile him, his wits forſake him, and he of a man become wormes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180713:13"/>meate, and that which the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gottes ſhall refuſe, ſhall rot &amp; ſtinke moſt horribly. Who could glory of his noble paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, or bragge of worſhipful predeceſſors, if he did remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that, <hi>Poſt miſerum funus &amp; vmbra ſumus.</hi> Surely if we did with the eyes of our conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, looke well into their graues, we ſhould find greater matter of confuſion then of glory. And if we did enter ſome what deeper into the matter, &amp; way in what eſtate their poore ſoules be in hell, we ſhould, I doubt not, haue greater cauſe to quake and tremble, then to bragge and boaſt of ſuch aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors.</p>
               <p>Where are now <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, <hi>Antiochus, Herod</hi> and other ſuch, whoſe prid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſurpaſſed ſo farre, as they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:180713:13"/>not aſhamed to take on them the title of gods? yea where are thoſe gods themſelues, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Iupiter, Mars, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, Bacchus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus, luno,</hi> and the reſt: where are they? their diuine fleſh and bones are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into dirt and duſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baruch.</hi> 3.</note> and their ſacred ſoules broyling in euerlaſting fire. Where are now all thoſe <hi>Caeſars</hi> and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours of Rome, who ſo many yeares together commaunded all the world, and ruled all the roſt? where are now all thoſe heathen kings, that in auncient times commaunded men and beaſts, which recreated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the birds and foules of the aire, which put their truſt and confidence in gold &amp; ſiluer, and neuer were ſatisfied in hoording vp of riches? <hi>Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minati ſunt, &amp; ad inferos deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180713:14"/>&amp; alif loco eorum ſurrex e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt.</hi> They are extermined periſhed and deſcended into hell, and others are riſen i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their roome.<note place="margin">Iob.</note> They paſſed the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dayes in all kind of dalliance &amp; delights, &amp; in a triſe deſcende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the gulfe of euerlaſting griefe, where perpetuall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and eternall horror doth inhabite and remaine.</p>
               <p>And who would ſet by worldly mucke and pelfe, if h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remembred theſe words of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sauiour:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou foole, this nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall they take thy ſoule fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thee, and the goods that tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> haſt gathered together, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall they be?</hi> Or who would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> feare to be clothed in Purple &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Veluet, and fare deliciouſly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day, if he remembred tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> which died <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> famine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.</note> was by the Angels ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180713:14"/>to heauen, and the rich glutton died and was buried in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell; or thought vppon theſe words of <hi>Dauid:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.</note> The rich men leaue their goods to aliens and ſtrangers, their graue muſt be their houſe for euer: <hi>Et vſque in eternum non videbunt lumen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lo here the laſt wil &amp; teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of worldly wiſe men, they giue their goods to ſtrangers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.</note> which ſpend them faſter then they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them, &amp; many times go together by the cares for the ſame, the diuel hath their ſoules, and the wormes their bodies: ô miſerable end! ô deteſtable te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament! what wiſe men liuing would not wiſh rather to liue &amp; die with <hi>Lazarus</hi> then with the rich glutton?</p>
               <p>What gaineth the Queenes moyles by their great burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſiluer, plate, &amp; other treaſures
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180713:15"/>wherewith they are loden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Surely nothing but a galle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> backe, for when they come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Inne, their treaſure is take from them, and they naked, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> red and galled, as they be, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> turned into the ſtable.</p>
               <p>So rich men gaine nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by their coffers, crammed wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Crownes, and ſackes full of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but a conſcience pittifu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> galled with many a grieuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> crime, &amp; when life is at an en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are by their friends ſtrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ped to their skinne, and nake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tyred, and galled as they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thruſt into the ſtinking ſtab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of hell, where they ſhall be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſed worſe then Moyles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Moyles in the ſtable ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> well dreſſed and curried, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſed with prouender, and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as much water as they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drinke: but the worldly r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:180713:15"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en in hell ſhall find none to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttie them, but millions of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls to torment them: they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all eate and gnaw their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſh for hunger, and if they would giue tenne thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orlds for one little drop of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld water,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.</note> they ſhall not haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Wel, liue a worlding he that will, <hi>Moriatur anima mea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orte Iuſtorum.</hi> God graunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to die the death of Iuſt men, and during life to thinke continually thereupon: The memory of death maketh vs humble, meeke, lowly, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, charitable, louing, cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and benigne, obedient to our ſuperiours, humble to our betters, lowly to our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals, meeke and benigne to our inferiours, ſubiects and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, charitable to the poore,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180713:16"/>louing to our neighbours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> courteous to all ſorts of peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as well ſtraungers as acqua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, poore as rich, foes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> friends.</p>
               <p>The memory of death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> keth vs chaſt and continent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and peaceable, watch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiſe and warie, compunct a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contrite, it mitigateth all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> moderate affections, and q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lifieth all inordinate paſſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> helpeth all diſeaſes of the min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and healeth all ſickneſſe of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſoule, it turneth imperfectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into perfections, and of gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinners maketh glorious Saints. And to conclude, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that attire themſelues by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Glaſſe, and ſpend their day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in meditating hereupon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> generations ſhall call the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bleſſed: <hi>&amp; in die malae liber ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um Dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus a ſagitta volan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:180713:16"/>indie, à negotio perambulantè in tenebr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s: ab incurſu, &amp; daemonio meridiano,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal</hi> 40.</note> In the euill day God ſhall deliuer them from the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that flveth by day, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>the buſie diuell that walketh by night, from in curſion and from the diuell that walketh euen at noone day, he that continually expecteth death, cannot but liue well, and hee that liueth well muſt needs die well: hee therefore that deſireth to liue and die well, let him beare well in mind that he is duſt, and into duſt he muſt returne again. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that which is already ſayd concerning this matter, might ſuffice any wiſe man or woman in the world, and cauſe them to looke to themſelues &amp; prepare for their dying day, yet for that I know many to be of ſuch groſſe and dull capacity
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:180713:17"/>as they cannot perceiue, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any thing, vnleſſe it be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch order ſet downe, as they may in a maner grope &amp; feel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the fame, I wil for their ſakes ſet before their eyes, the lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table complaint of one attached by death, long before hee looked for him or imagined him to by ſo neere: wiſhing all men that reade the ſame, grace and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to beware leaſt the like alſo happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, which God defend.</p>
               <p>This man in the flower o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his time fell ſo ſicke, as both Phiſitions and all other his friends thought him but a dead man, &amp; willed him to prepare himſelfe for God, the which when he heard, it did ſo ama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him, as for a long time hee could not vtter one word, his griefe was ſo great, and his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:180713:17"/>feare ſo farre ſurpaſſed al mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: at the laſt with great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of teares, which like to litle ſtreames trickled down his cheekes, he burſt foorth into theſe or the like words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Ah cruell death, how haſt thou intrapped me: how am I entangled in thy ſnares, that thought my ſelfe farre out of thy reach? I imagined that I had yet many yeares to liue &amp; a long race to runne: but alas my Glaſſe is runne out, and my dayes are vaniſhed like a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</note> 
                  <hi>Timor &amp; tremor vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſuper me, &amp; contexerunt me tenebrae.</hi> The feare of death hath oppreſſed me, in the gulfe of endleſſe griefe am I dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched, and the ſorrowes of hell haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed me about, and hemd me in on euery ſide,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.</note> there is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180713:18"/>no hope of recouery, no helpe, no refuge,<note place="margin">Pſalm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> no way to eſcape, but needs muſt I end my dayes in deepe diſpaire, and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame miſerie:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</note> my youthfull dayes are vaniſhed like ſmoke, my bones are drie as ſtickes, my fleſh withered like haye, &amp; my hart parched vp, for that I haue forgotten to cate my meate; thus am I ſuddenly brought to naught, that thought my ſelfe no ſmall man in the view of the world.</p>
               <p>Ah curſed world, wo be to me that euer I followed thy vanities;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.</note> wo, wo, ten thouſand times that euer I knew thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ah God, how happie had I bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> if I had neuer bene borne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> How happy if I had dyed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my mothers wombe, and ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> carried from her bellie to my graue?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 41.</note> O death how grieuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:180713:18"/>is the remembrance of thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a man, whoſe pleaſure and onely felicity is ſet on worldly vanities, as mine was? I could neuer abide to thinke on thee, but now I am inforced to feele thee to mine inexplicable paine and remedileſſe griefe: I would not hearken to thoſe that gaue me good counſell, but counted them fooles, that liued continually looking for death, perſwading my ſelfe that I ſhould liue <hi>Methuſalems</hi> yeares. But now alas, though it be late, I find no foole in the world comparable to me: For Death at vnawares is ruſhed vppon me, he hath areſted me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound me with inſolluble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands, and draweth me to hell, euen as a hang-man draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th a condemned man to the gallowes; Helpe, helpe, helpe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:180713:19"/>Father, Mother, Brethren, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Wife, Children, Friends, Kinsfolkes, helpe, helpe me, if euer you doe lone me, now helpe me: <hi>Miſereminimei, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni mes, ſalt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m vos amic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mes,</hi> Take pitty vpon me, take pittie vpon me,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.</note> at leaſt you my eſpecial good friends, take pitty vppon me, keepe me from thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruell murderer, defend m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from this terrible Tyger, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me from this ramping and roaring Lyon, which bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me in his pawes: and is rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> die to teare me in pee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Alas, alas, will no man helpe what none? O death ſpare m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I pray thee take my lands an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let me liue, for the loue of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord whome I ſerue, lot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alone for a yeare, for a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> neth, for a day, for an h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wer, giue me a little ſpace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:180713:19"/>repent I beſeech thee.</p>
               <p>Tut, tut, thou art the child of Death, thou art condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to die, thy hower is ended, and thou muſt die, no parents, no friends, no kindred, no trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, no honour, no wit, no pollicie can preuaile or helpe thee a whit. If thou wouldeſt giue me this world full of gold for one howers ſpace, I would not take it. And if all the Kings, Queenes and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors that are now, or euer were in the world, ſhould on their knees intreate for the lengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy life one <hi>Miſerere</hi> while, I would not heare them, but euen as I now find thee, ſo wil I preſent thee before the tribunall ſeate of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſpatch away.</p>
               <p>O moſt curſed and cruell death! O moſt bloudy and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tileſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180713:20"/>butcher. Ah God, whoſe mieſerie is comparable to mine?</p>
               <p>Youth (quoth Death) no words will preuaile, thy ſobs and ſighes, thy lamentable out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries and pittifull complaints, thy wringing of hands, and tearing of thine haire doe not moue me a whit, but forth with will I bring thee to a place where thou ſhalt feele &amp; proue ſuch things, as neither thine eyes haue ſeene, nor thy eare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue hard, nor thy hart can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue or imagine: thou haddeſt time enough to haue ſeene this hower, haddeſt thou bin wiſe, but had I wiſt commeth now too late.</p>
               <p>Ah cruelll death, whithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt I go, alas, whither wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou leade me? to a land vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of vtter darknes,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:180713:20"/>a land of endleſſe miſerie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 67.</note> where I ſhall liue depriued of all my worldly pleaſures, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall any man liuing ſee me againe?</p>
               <p>But to what ende doe I ſtand intreating of him that is paſt all pity? Better were it for me to ſpend the litle ſpace that yet remaineth, in bewayling my time, which I haue moſt vnprofitably ſpent. O that I had now a ſea of brackiſh tears to runne downe my cheekes, for after this hower my teares will neuer be meritorious any more. Ah God how haue I loſt, how haue I neglected, how haue I miſpent my gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den time, in vaine and wanton ſpeeches, in banqueting and chambering, in dauncing and dallying, in dicing and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in bibbing and bouſing,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180713:21"/>in ſleeping compaſſe, and a thouſand other ſuch villaines, in which ſeeing my ſolace I haue vtterly loſt my ſelfe, and hunting after tranſitorie plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, I haue found eternall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and paines. Alas why did I not while I might, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour ſo to liue as I might not haue feared to die, (for ſure I am, that he that liueth well can not chuſe but die well:) why had I not all my life long made preperation for this iournie, in which ſo many millions of men periſh, as ſcarce one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ten thouſand paſſe to the end in ſafety: Oh, oh moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie I, alas, alas, in what danger do I ſtand, if my foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting faile me now, I periſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually: Ah miſerable wretch that I am, all this as yet is but the preface or prologue to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180713:21"/>play, all that as yet I feele is but a ſhadow or dum ſhew of that which preſently muſt follow, and if the prologue be ſo dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, alas how terrible will the Tragedie it ſelfe be? If the very ſhadow and feare of death be ſo horrible as it wholly ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth me to thinke thereupon, oh God what will death it ſelfe be? In what ſort ſhall I appeare and ſtand before the face of that moſt iuſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere iudge, whom and in whoſe ſight I haue offended more then a hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thouſand times, and that moſt hainouſly? I was ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this world to ſerue my Lord God, my creatour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, in faſting, praying and the like, but I alas haue conſumed my time in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the quite contrarie. In
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:180713:22"/>turning faſting into feaſting, praying into prating, vertues into vices and all miſdeedes whatſoeuer, &amp; of all the dayes of my life God onely knoweth whether I haue ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t either one day or hower in his ſeruice to his liking or not.</p>
               <p>Alas with what ſhame and confuſion ſhall I ſtand before God and his Angels, when I ſhall be driueu to giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of euery idle word that I haue ſpoken in my dayes, what a reckening am I like to make? Alas I am not able to number the thouſandth part of the mortall crimes that I haue committed, what then can I ſay for my idle words and thoughts, which in number ſurmounte the ſandes of the Sea?</p>
               <p>Ah miſerable foole that I am
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:180713:22"/>I ſhould haue thought of theſe things before, but now alas it is too late, wo, wo to me tenne thouſand times, that euer I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred my time of amendment, putting off from day to day, crying with the Crow, <hi>Cras, Cras,</hi> ſo long as now I am like to bee the Diuels owne blacke bird, and to be put vp in the Cage of hell for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
               <p>O falſe fawning and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring friends, ô couſening and craftie Phyſitions, how iuſt cauſe haue I to wiſh, that I had neuer knowne nor ſeene you? you told me all was well, and that there was no daunger of death at all: Feare nothing ſaid you, this infirmity is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a litle diſtemperature of ſome humors, and therefore thou needeſt not ſend for the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:180713:23"/>Preacher, or to trouble your ſelfe with thinking on your ſinnes at this time, but when you are well, confeſſe your ſinnes vnto God at leaſure, at this time ſleepe, take your reſt and ſet all your cares apart you ſhall ſoone be whole o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this maladie. O falſe and moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnfaithfull friends: friends fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I? nay rather moſt cruell foe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enemies of my poore ſoule, and workers of my euerlaſting wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and miſerie, for hearkening to your Syren ſongs, I haue ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed on the rockes of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting death, &amp; I periſh whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is none to helpe: but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> las, I am well enough ſerued for he that will not preuen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> death, is worthie to be preue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him.</p>
               <p>All mortall wights of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſexe or degree ſoeuer thou b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:180713:23"/>remember that thou muſt die, and perhaps as ſoone as my ſelfe, for anie warrant that thou haſt to the contrarie; do good to all while thou mayeſt, ſeeke to appeaſe the wrath of God: while you haue time, in Hymnes, Pſalmes and Thankſgiuing ſeeke to praiſe, and pleaſe him, and while thou liueſt in this wretched world, liue in ſuch ſort as in the houre of death you die not in ſuch confuſion and as I do now. I wiſh now that I had ſpent my youth in the wilderneſſe with <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> liued by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rie bread and water with <hi>Mach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rius,</hi> prayed with <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>mes,</hi> vntill my knees had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in as hard as horne, bewayled my ſins with <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne,</hi> whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual teares had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>et to furrowes or gutters in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:180713:24"/>her face, beaten my ſelfe wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> an yron chaine thriſe a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vntill the bloud ranne dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the ground, as <hi>Kather<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enna</hi> did, and done an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing elſe whatſouer, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> might liue any longer, I wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> liue euen like an Angell vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> earth, but alas I would n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> when I might, and now I ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not though I would. Let eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> rie one therefore if he be wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> beware by my harmes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> while yeares, ſtrength, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> time do ſerue to merite, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> deuour to preuent the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cares and moſt perillo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perplexities that you ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lapped in. Behold, I ſtand no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in ſuch extremitie, as I ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> greater account, and wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> more reioyce of one <hi>Pater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> or other litle prayer d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly ſaid for me, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:180713:24"/>innumerable, millions of gold and precious ſtones. I haue with the prodigall child, ſpent my golden time, and waſted all laſciuiouſly, not thinking what would follow, and now I go a begging from dore to dore, crauing ſome ſpirituall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mes, and euerie one thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth me from him, ſaying:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne forte nobis, &amp; tibi non fufficiat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 15.</note> I would gladly catch ſome of the crummes that fall from their table, but no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will giue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e anie, no man hath pitie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e; and rightly, for why ſhould any man pitie him that would not pitie himſelfe? I cared not for my ſelfe, why then ſhould others care for me?</p>
               <p>O all you that ſtand here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me, and are eye-witneſſes of my preſent miſeries, beware, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ware by me, and while you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:180713:25"/>are in health, hoord not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your treaſurers in earth, but heauen, let poore mens b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſomes be your ſtore-houſe Redeeme your ſinnes w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Almes-deedes, and your i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quities with pitie of the poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> endeuor by the means of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ked Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, that in the houre of de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they may bring you richly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> den with merites and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> workes into the eternall tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nacle, and be not excluded ſhut out for want of g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without hope of mercie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fauour, as ye ſee me.</p>
               <p>Oh, oh, cruell death I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath pierced my hart, the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of my diſſolution is come, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liue no longer, my ſight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> xeth dimme, my ſenſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> my tong beginneth to cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to the roofe of my mouth,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:180713:25"/>voyce waxeth feeble, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed of ſpeaking, I begin to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>attle in the throate. Ah tole, go tole my dolefull paſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell. Ring out my mournfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nell. Alas, alas, I muſt be gone, I muſt die, I muſt die, farewell my faithfull friends, &amp; all the things that in this world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tooke delight in; I muſt now depart and leaue you all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind. <hi>Adue, Adue</hi> for euer and euer, I ſhall neuer ſee you againe. Behold, my legs waxe cold as yce, my hands withered and drie, my nayles blacke, my face wanne, pale, earthly, my ſight dimme and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arke, mine eyes waxe hollow &amp; begin to roll in my head, and more and more I waxe loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to looke on, my heart panteth and gaſpeth for breath,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:180713:26"/>but being oppreſſed by dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it can indure no longer, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all my carnall friends begin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> put me in mind of God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will me to call vpon Ieſus, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to runne to him for mercie. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> las, how can I with confiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now cal vpon him whom I n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uer ſerued? how can I hope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mercie at his hands, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue ſo infinitly offended? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ring life I abuſed his mercy, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> therefore muſt I now feele h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iuſtice. <hi>O Arſenius, Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> how happie and bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wert thou, that haddeſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> houre of death alwayes befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thine eyes. But wo, and tenn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thouſand times wo to me, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> neuer thought on death<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vntill I was wounded at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart.</p>
               <p>Alas, whither ſhall my poor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:180713:26"/>ghoſt go now? what harbour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>all my ſinfull ſoule find? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ho will receiue her? who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>all be her companion? who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al be her guide in this ſtrange <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gion by the which ſhe is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſe? who will or can helpe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r? or what is he that dareth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeake for her, departing as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e doth? O lord God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſtes, thou art our guide, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t the way by which I ſhould walke, thou art the doore by which I muſt enter; be thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y refuge, my comfort, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efence in this moſt dreadfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oure: thou art the Father of mercie, and God of all conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation and comfort, it is more proper to thee to haue mercie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en for me to ſinne; I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inne ſo much, but thou canſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orgiue much more: and this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:180713:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:180713:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:180713:28"/>I also beleeue, that I ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more offend thy Maieſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſpairing of thy mercie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in all the other ſinnes that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> I committed, and there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will I put my truſt in thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> though thou ſhouldeſt kill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Miſerere mei Deus, miſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> met, quta in te confidit an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mea.</hi> Into thy hands, ô Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do I commend my ſoule, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>redeemed me, ô Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of truth.</p>
               <p>Ah farewell, farewell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> friends, God graunt my m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and vnprouided de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may make you to liue and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> better then I haue done, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> manie legions of wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rits which enuiron me ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> about, triumphing the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my ſoule, hoping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> haue me their perpetuall ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:180713:28"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hel. All good Chriſtians pray or me, that God of his infinite goodneſſe deliuer me not ouer to the willes of thoſe moſt horrible and vgly monſters.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:180713:29"/>
            <head>A SONG IN THE praiſe of heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>HIeruſalem</hi> my happie home,</l>
               <l>When ſhall I come to thee?</l>
               <l>When ſhall my ſorowes haue an end?</l>
               <l>Thy ioyes when ſhall I ſee?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O happie harbour of the Saints,</l>
               <l>O ſweet and pleaſant ſoile:</l>
               <l>In thee no ſorrow may be found,</l>
               <l>No griefe, no care, no toile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In thee no ſickneſſe may be ſeene,</l>
               <l>No hurt, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, no ſore:</l>
               <l>There is no death, not vgly diuell,</l>
               <l>Theres life for euermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No dampiſh miſt is ſeene in thee,</l>
               <l>No cold, nor darkeſome night:</l>
               <l>There euerie ſoule ſhines like the Sun,</l>
               <l>There God himſelfe giues light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There luſt and luker cannot dwel,</l>
               <l>There enuie beares no ſway:</l>
               <l>There is no hunger, hear, nor cold,</l>
               <l>But pleaſure euerie way.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:180713:29"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ther's <hi>Nectar</hi> and <hi>Ambroſia</hi> made,</l>
               <l>Ther's <hi>muſke</hi> and <hi>Ciuet</hi> ſweet:</l>
               <l>There many a fine and daintie drugge</l>
               <l>Are troden vnder feete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There <hi>Cinamon,</hi> there <hi>Sugar</hi> growes,</l>
               <l>There <hi>Nard</hi> and <hi>Balme</hi> abound:</l>
               <l>What toung can tell, or heart conceiue</l>
               <l>The ioyes that there are found?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quite through the ſtreets with ſiluer ſound</l>
               <l>The floud of life doth flow,</l>
               <l>Vpon whoſe bankes on euery ſide</l>
               <l>The wood of life doth grow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There trees do euermore beare fruite</l>
               <l>And euermore do ſpring:</l>
               <l>There euermore the Angels ſit,</l>
               <l>And euermore do ſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtands with harpe inhand,</l>
               <l>As maiſter of the quire:</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand times that man were bleſt</l>
               <l>That might his mufike heare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gods praiſes there are alwayes ſong,</l>
               <l>With harmonie moſt ſweete:</l>
               <l>Old <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>meon</hi> and <hi>Zacharie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Haue not their ſongs to ſeeke.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:180713:30"/>
            <lg>
               <l>There <hi>Magdalene</hi> hath left her mone,</l>
               <l>And cheerefully doth ſing</l>
               <l>With bleſſed Saints, whoſe harmonie</l>
               <l>In euery ſtreete doth ring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> my happie home,</l>
               <l>Would God I were in thee,</l>
               <l>Would God my woes were at an end,</l>
               <l>Thy ioyes that I may ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:30"/>
            <head>AN EXHORTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to good life.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the puniſhmentes which the Lord threatneth vnto ſuch as liue a ſinfull life. Chap. I.</head>
               <p>ONe of the principal means which the Lord hath vſed often times to bridle the hearts of men, and to draw them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the obedience of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, hath bene to ſet before their eyes the horrible plagues and puniſhments, that are prepared for ſuch perſons as be rebels, and tranſgreſſors of his lawe: for although the hope of the rewardes that are promiſed to the good in the life to come, may moue vs very much hereunto, yet are we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly more moued with things
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:180713:31"/>that be irkeſome vnto vs, than with things that be pleaſant: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as we ſee by dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that we are vexed more with an iniurie done vnto vs, than delighted with any honor: and we are more troubled with ſickneſſe, than comforted with health: and ſo by the diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of ſickeneſſe we come to vnderſtand the commoditie of health: as by a thing ſo much the better perceiued, by how much more it is ſenſibly felt. Nowe for this cauſe did the Lorde in times paſt vſe this, meanes more then any other, as it appeareth moſt clearely by the writings of the Prophets, which are euery where full of dreadfull ſaying and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hy the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arily vſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reatnings.</note> wherwith the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to put a terror into the hearts of men, and ſo to bridle
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:180713:31"/>&amp; ſubdue them vnder the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his law: and for this end he commaunded the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>leremie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 36.2.</note> that hee ſhould take a white booke, and write in the ſame all the threatnings and calamities which he had reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him, euen from the firſt day he began to talke with him, vntill that preſent houre: and that hee ſhould reade the ſame in the preſence of all the people, to ſee if peraduenture they would be mooued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to repentance &amp; to cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge their former life, to the end that he might alſo change the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of his wrath, which he had purpoſed to execute vpon them: and the holy Scripture ſayth, That when the Prophet had done according as he was commaunded by Almightie God, and had read all thoſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:180713:32"/>threatnings in the preſence of the people, and of the Rulers, there aroſe ſuch a feare and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them, that they were all aſtoniſhed, and as it were beſtraught of their wits, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one in anothers face, for the exceeding great feare which they had conceiued of thoſe wordes.</p>
               <p>This was one of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal meanes that Almighty God vſed with men in the time of the law written, and ſo did hee alſo in the time of the lawe of grace; in which the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om</hi> 1.</note> that as there is reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a iuſtice whereby God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men iuſt, ſo is there alſo reuealed an indignation and wrath, wherwith he puniſheth the vniuſt. For which cauſe Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous forerunner of our Sauiour
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:180713:32"/>Chriſt, was ſent with this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion &amp; embaſſage, to preach vnto the worlde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>verſe</hi> 10. <hi>luke</hi> 3.9.</note> that <hi>the axe was now put to the roote of the tree, and that euery tree that brought not foorth good fruite ſhould be cut downe, and caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire.</hi> He ſayd moreouer, that <hi>there was another come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world more mightie then he, that caried in his hande a fanne, to winnow &amp; clenſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his flower, and that hee would put vp his corne into his garnard, but the chaffe he would burne in a fire that ſhould neuer be quenched.</hi> This was the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and embaſſage, which the holy fore-runner of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt brought into the worlde, and ſo great was the thunder of theſe wordes, and the terrour which entred into mens hearts ſo dreadfull, that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:180713:33"/>there ran vnto him of all ſtate and conditions of men, euen o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the very Phariſees and Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, yea and ſouldiers alſo (which of all others are woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be moſt diſſolute, &amp; to hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leaſt care of their conſcience and each of them for himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> demaunded particularly of the holy man, what he ſhould d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to attaine vnto ſaluation, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to eſcape thoſe terrible threa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which he had denounce vnto them: ſo great was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feare they had conceiued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them.</p>
               <p>Now this is that (my dear Chriſtian brother) which I do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at this preſent in the behalfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Almightie God preach vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee, although not with ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feruencie of ſpirit, and like ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lines of life, yet (that which in porteth more to this caſe) wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:180713:33"/>the ſame truth, and certaintie: for ſo much as the faith and Goſpel that Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> preached at that time, was no other, but this which we preach at this preſent.</p>
               <p>Now if thou be deſirous to vnderſtand in few words, how great the puniſhment is, that Almightie God hath threatned in his holy Scriptures to the wicked, that which may moſt briefely and moſt to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe be ſaide in this matter, is this: that like as the rewarde of the good is an vniuerſall good thing, euen ſo the puniſhment of the wicked is an vniuerſall euill, which comprehendeth in it all the euils that are. For the better vnderſtanding whereof it is to be noted, that all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils of this life are particular e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, and therefore doe not tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:180713:34"/>all our ſenſes generally, but onely one or ſome of them. As taking an example of the diſeaſes of our bodie,<note place="margin">The miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this life are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</note> wee ſee that one hath a diſeaſe in his eies, another in his eares, one is ſicke in his heart, another in his ſtomacke, ſome other in his head, and ſo diuerſe men are diſeaſed in diuerſe parts: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in ſuch wiſe, that none of all theſe diſeaſes bee generally throughout all the members of the bodie, but particular to ſome one of them. And yet for all this we ſee what griefe onely one of theſe diſeaſes may put vs vnto, and howe painefull a night the ſicke man hath in any one of theſe infirmities, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be nothing elſe but a litle ache in one tooth. Now let vs put the caſe, that there were ſome one man ſicke of ſuch an
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:180713:34"/>vniuerſall diſeaſe, that hee had no part of his bodie, neither any one ioynt or ſenſe free from his proper griefe and torment, but that at one time and inſtant he ſuffered moſt exceeding ſharpe paines in his head, in his eyes and eares, in his teeth and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make, in his liuer and heart, and to be ſhort, in all the reſt of the members and ioynts of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and that hee lay after this ſort ſtretching himſelfe in his bed, pained with theſe griefes and torments, euery member of his bodie hauing his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar torment, he I ſay, that ſhold lie thus pained, and afflicted, how great torment and griefe of minde, thinke ye, ſhould he ſuſtaine? O what thing could any man imagine more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and more worthy of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion? Surely if thou ſholdeſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:180713:35"/>ſee but a dogge ſo tormented the ſtreete,<note place="margin">How the damned are tormented in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell.</note> his very paines wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moue thee to pittie him. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this is that (my deere Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> brother, if any compariſon m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be made between them) which is ſuffered in that curſed hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place of hell, not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſpace of one night, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> uerlaſtingly, for euer and eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. For like as the wicked haue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fended Almightie God with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their members and ſenſes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> haue made armour of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſerue ſinne: euen ſo will h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ordaine that they ſhall there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all tormented each one of the with his proper torment:<note place="margin">Eyes.</note> the ſhall the wanton and lechero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eyes be torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rible ſight of diuels:<note place="margin">Eares.</note> the ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with the confuſion of ſuch ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rible cries, and lamentations ſhall there be heard:<note place="margin">Noſe.</note> the no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:180713:35"/>with the intollerable ſtench of that filthy and lothſome place: the taſte,<note place="margin">Taſte.</note> with a moſt rauenous hunger and thirſt: the touching,<note place="margin">Touching.</note> and all the members of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, with extreame colde and fire: the imagination,<note place="margin">Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> ſhall bee tormented by conceiuing of griefes preſent: the memorie,<note place="margin">Memorie.</note> by calling to minde the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures paſt: the vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> by conſidering what benefites are left, and what miſeries are to come. This multitude of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes the holy Scripture ſignifieth vnto vs, when it faith, that <hi>in hell there ſhall be hunger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>thirſt, weering, wailing, gnaſhing of teeth: ſwordes double edged, ſpirits created for reuengement, ſerpents, worms, ſcorpions, ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and wormewood, water of gall, the ſpirit of tempeſt,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things of like ſort. Wherby
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:180713:36"/>are ſignified vnto vs, as in a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, the multitude and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full terror of the moſt horrible paines and torments, that be in that curſed place, there ſhall be like wiſe darkeneſſe, both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward, both of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule: farre more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure then the darkeneſſe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.</note> which might be felt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with hands. There ſhall be fire alſo, &amp; not as this fire here that tormenteth a litle, &amp; ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeth, but ſuch a fire as that place requireth, which tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth exceedingly, and ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer make an end of torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting. Now if this be true, what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wonder can there be, than that they which beleeue and confeſſe this for trueth, ſhould liue with ſuch a ſtrange negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and careleſneſſe as they doe? What trauailes and paines
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:180713:36"/>would not a man willingly take to eſcape euen one onely day, yea one houre, the very leaſt of all theſe torments? And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do they not then to eſcape the euerlaſtingneſſe of ſo great paines, &amp; horrible torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſo litle a trauell, as to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the exerciſe of vertue? Surely the conſideration of this matter were able to make a man beſides himſelfe, in caſe he would deepely weigh it.</p>
               <p>And if among ſo great a number of paines,<note place="margin">The dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned have no kind of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, or hope of any caſe, or end of their moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> there were any maner of hope of ende or releaſe, it would be ſome kinde of comfort: but alas it is not ſo, for there the gates are faſt ſhut vp from all expectation of anie maner of eaſe, or hope: in all kind of paines, and calamities that be in this world, there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſome gappe lying open,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:180713:37"/>whereby the patient may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ceiue ſome kinde of comfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſometimes reaſon, ſometime the weather, ſometimes friendes, ſometimes the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that others are troubled w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the very ſame diſeaſe, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at the leaſt the hope of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> end, may cheere him ſomewh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Onely in theſe moſt horri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> paines and miſeries that bee hell, all the wayes are ſhut vp ſuch ſort, and all the hauen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> comfort ſo embarred, that miſerable ſinner cannot he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for remedie on any ſide, neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of heauen, nor of earth, neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the time paſt, or preſent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the time to come, neither by any other meanes. The da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſoules thinke that all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are ſhooting darts at them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that all creatures haue con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt them, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:180713:37"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y themſelues are cruell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nſt themſelues. To this may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e applied that ſaying of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly Prophet <hi>Dauid:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.6.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>wes of bill haue compaſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> round about, and the ſnares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>death haue beſieged mee.</hi> For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſide ſo euer they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke, or turne their eyes, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe continually behold occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions of ſorrowe and griefe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd none at all of any eaſe, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omfort.<note place="margin">Mat. 25.10.</note> The <hi>wiſe Virgines</hi> ſayeth the Euangeliſt) <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>loode readie prepared at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ates of the bridegroome entred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and the gate was foorthwith locked.</hi> O locking euerlaſting! O incloſure immortall! O gate of all goodneſſe, which ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er any more be opened again, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> if he had ſaid more plainely, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e gate of pardon, and mercie, of comfort, of interceſſion, of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:180713:38"/>hope, of grace, and of all go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> neſſe is ſhut vp for euer and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uer. Sixe dayes &amp; no more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Manna to be gathered, but ſeuenth day,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.</note> which was the both day, there was none to found, and therefore ſhall faſt for euer, that hath not due time made his prouiſion forehand. The ſluggard (ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the wiſe man) will not till ground for feare of colde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> therefore ſhall hee begge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bread in ſommer, and no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall giue him to eate, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> an other place he faith: <hi>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> gathereth in ſommer is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſonne, and hee that giueth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſelfe to ſleeping at that ſeaſon the ſonne of confuſion.</hi> For w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> confuſion can there be great then that which that miſera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> couetous riche man ſuffer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> who with a fewe crumme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:180713:38"/>bread that fell from his table, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight haue purchaſed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fe abundance of euerlaſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elicitie, and glorie in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome of heauen: but becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e would not giue ſo ſmall a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning, he came to ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eame neceſſitie, that he beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, yea and ſhall for euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>gge, but onely the droppe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>colde water, and ſhall neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>taine it: who is not mooued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ith that requeſt of this infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nate damned perſon, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ryed: <hi>O father Abraham, haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>mpaſſion vpon me, &amp; ſend La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arus vnto mee, that hee may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ppe the tippe of his finger in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ater, and touch my tongue, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſe horrible flames doe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me exceedingly.</hi> What ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r requeſt could there be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> then this? hee durſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueſt ſo much as one cuppe of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:180713:39"/>water, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>either that <hi>Laza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſhould put this whole handing the water, not yet (which more to be wondre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d at) did requeſt ſo much as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> finger, but onely the tip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed that it might touch his to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and yet this onely would be graunted vnto him, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> by thou maieſt perceiue, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> faſt the ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of all conſolation ſhut vp, and howe vniuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that interdict and excommu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cation is, which is there laid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on the damned, fith this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> glutton could not obtaine much as this ſmall requeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that where ſoeuer the damn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perſons do turn their eies, &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which ſide ſoeuer they ſire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> forth their hands, they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> finde any maner of comfort, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neuer ſo ſmall, and as he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is in the ſea choked, and almo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:180713:39"/>drowned vnder the water, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inding any ſtay wherewith to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ttle his foot, ſtretcheth forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is handes often times on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſide in vaine, (becauſe all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he graſpeth after is thinne and liquid water, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth him) euen ſo ſhall it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re with the damned perſons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en they ſhall be drowned in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat deepe ſea of ſo many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies, where they ſhall ſtriue and ſtruggle alwayes with death, without finding any ſuccour or place of ſtay, whereupon they may reſt themſelues. Now this is one of the greateſt paines wherewith they be tormented in that curſed place. For if theſe torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſhould haue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance limited but for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine time, though it were for a thouſand, yea, a hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand millions of yeres, yet euen
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:180713:40"/>this would bee ſome litle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto them, for nothing perfectly great in caſe it hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an end, but alas, they haue no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo much as this poore and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable comfort, but contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wiſe, their paines are equall continuance with the eterni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Almightie God,<note place="margin">In hell ſhall be no end of torment.</note> and the ſting of their miſerie, with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eternitie of Gods glory: as lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as Almightie God ſhall liue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> long ſhall they die: and whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Almightie God ſhall ceaſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> bee God, then ſhall they all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ceaſe to be as they are. O dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life! O immortall death! know not whether I may true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tearme thee either life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> death: for if thou be life, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doeſt thou kill? and if thou be death, how doeſt thou endure wherefore I will call thee ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one, nor the other: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:180713:40"/>ſo much as in both of them there is contained ſome that is good, as in life there is reſt, and in death there is an end (which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a great comfort to the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted:) but thou haſt neither reſt nor end: what art thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Marie, thou art the worſt of life, and the worſt of death, for of death thou haſt the torment without end, and of life thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt the continuance without any reſt. Almightie God hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poyled both life and death of that good which they had, and hath put in thee, that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emained to be a puniſhment or the wicked. O bitter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſition! ô vnſauerie purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of the Lords cup,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.</note> of the which all the ſinners of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth ſhall drinke their part.</p>
               <p>Now in this continuance, in his eternity, I would wiſh that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:180713:41"/>thou (my deare Chriſtian bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) wouldeſt fixe the eyes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy conſideration a litle while &amp; that as the cleane beaſt che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth her cud, euen ſo tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wouldeſt chew and weigh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> point within thy ſelf with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deliberation: and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thou maiſt do it the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, conſider a litle the pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that a ſicke man abideth in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuill night, eſpecially if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vexed with anie vcheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or ſharpe diſeaſe: marke ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> often he tumbleth and toſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his bed, what diſquietneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hehath, how long and tedio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> one night ſeemeth vnto hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how duly he counteth all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> houres of the clocke, and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> long he thinketh each of the to be, how he paſſeth the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in wiſhing for the dawning the day, which notwithſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:180713:41"/>ding is like to helpe him verie litle towards the curing of his diſeaſe. If this then be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo great a torment, what a torment ſhall that be (trow ye) in that euerlaſting night in hell, which hath no morning, nor ſo much as anie hope of dawning of the day? O darkneſſe moſt obſcure! ô night euerlaſting! ô night accurſed euen by the mouth of Almightie God, and of all his Saints: that one ſhall wiſh for light, and ſhall neuer ſee, neither ſhall the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the morning ariſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie more; conſider then, what a kind of torment that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall be, to liue euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y in ſuch a night as this is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing not in a ſoft bed, (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſicke man doth) but in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te burning furnace foming
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:180713:42"/>out ſuch terrible raging flames what ſhoulders ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to abide theſe horrible heates? Oh how it maketh ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euen to tremble &amp; quake, only to thinke of it! If it ſeeme to vs thing intollerable, to haue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome part of our feet ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon a panne of burning coales for the ſpace of ſaying one <hi>Pater noster,</hi> what ſhall be (trowe ye) to ſtand body and ſoule, burning in the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſt of thoſe euerlaſting h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging fiers in hell, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon whereof the fiers of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> world are but painted fires! there any wit or iudgement this world? haue men th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> right ſenſes? do they vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what theſe words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> import? or are they peradue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture perſwaded, that theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> onely fables of Poets? or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:180713:42"/>they thinke that this apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth vnto them, or elſe that it was meant onely for others? none of all this can they ſay, for ſo much as our faith aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth vs certainely herein: and our Sauiour Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who is the euerlaſting truth, cryeth out in his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.35 <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. 31.</note> ſaying: <hi>Heauen and earth ſhall faile, but my word ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of this miſerie there follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth an other, as great as it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Section.</hi> 3. <hi>The paines of hell conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in one degree.</hi>
                  </note> which is, that the paynes are alwayes continuing in one like being, and in one ſame degree, without anie manner of intermiſſion, or decreaſing. All maner of things that are vnder the cope of heauen, do moue and turne round about with the ſame heauen, and do neuer ſtand ſtill at one ſtate
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:180713:43"/>or being: but are continually either aſcending or deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding. The ſea and the riuers haue their ebbing and flowing, the times, the ages, and the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fortune of men &amp; of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, are euermore in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall motion, there is no ſeue ſo feruent, that doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline; neither griefe ſo ſharpe but that after it is much aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, it doth forthwith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. To be ſhort, all the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations and miſeries are by litle and litle worne away with time: and as the common ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, nothing is ſooner drie vp then teares, only that pain in hell is alwayes greene: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that feuer neuer decreaſeth onely that extremitie of hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knoweth not what is either euening or morning. In the time of <hi>Noes</hi> floud Almight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:180713:43"/>God rained fortie dayes and fortie nights continually with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing vpon the earth; and this ſufficed to drowne the whole world, but in that place of torment in hell there ſhall raine euerlaſting ſpeares, and darts of furie vpon that curſed land, without euer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſo much as one onely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and this is ſo true, that as (faith a Schoole-man) euen the paines which ſhall be there giuen for the ſmalleſt ſinnes, ſhall be likewiſe euerlaſting, aſwell as thoſe paines which be there preſcribed for the greateſt and moſt hainous ſins, for infinite puniſhment is due vnto all ſinnes, becauſe in the eſtate of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation there is no abſolution or diſcharge of anie debt,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:180713:44"/>(for that the time of paying and ſatisfying is then paſt) ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall the paine due vnto veniall ſinne continue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in one ſame eſtate, and ſhall neuer ceaſe. Now what torment can be greater and more to be abhorred, then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to ſuffer after one like maner without any kind of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration or change, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meate be neuer ſo delicate yet in caſe we feed continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereupon, it will in verie ſhort time be verie lothſome vnto vs: for no meate can be more precious and delicate, then that Manna was, which almightie God ſent to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell in the deſert, and yet becauſe they did eate continually thereof, it made them to lothe it, yea, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked them to vomite it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:180713:44"/>The way that is al plaine (they ſay) wearieth more then anie other, becauſe alwayes the varietie (yea euen in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) is a kind of comfort. Tell me then of good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, if things that be pleaſant and ſauorie, when they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes after one maner, are an occaſion of lothſomneſſe and paine, what kind of lothſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will that be, which ſhall be cauſed by thoſe moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble paines, &amp; torments in hell, which do continue euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly after one like ſort: what will the damned and curſed creatures thinke, when they ſhall there ſee themſelues ſo vtterly abhorred, and forſaken of Almighty God, that he will not ſo much as with the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of one ſmall ſin, mitigate ſomewhat their torment? ſo
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:180713:45"/>great ſhall the furie and rage be which they ſhal there conceiue againſt him, that they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe continually to curſe and blaſpheme his holy name.</p>
               <p>Vnto all theſe paines there is alſo added the paine of that euerlaſting conſumer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Section.</hi> 4. <hi>The worme of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. Eſay.</hi> 66. <hi>verſe.</hi> 24.</note> which is the worme of conſcience, whereof the holy Scripture makes oftentimes mention, ſaying: <hi>Their worme ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer die: and their fire ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be quenched.</hi> This worme is a furious raging deſpight, &amp; a bitter repentance without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fruit, which the wicked ſhall haue alwayes in hell, by calling to their remembrance the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie and time they had whiles they were in this world to eſcape: theſe moſt grieuous and horrible torments, &amp; how they would not vſe the benefit
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:180713:45"/>therof, &amp; therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinner ſeeth himſelf thus tormented and vexed on euery ſide, and calleth to mind how manie dayes and years he hath ſpent idlely in vanities, in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, and pleaſures, and how oftentimes he was aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of this perill, and how litle regard he toke thereof. What ſhall he thinke? what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh &amp; ſorrow ſhall there be in his he art? haſt thou not read in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 13</note> that <hi>there ſhall be weeping, and wayling and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> Now theſe &amp; others the like ſhall be the cauſes of this ſo great &amp; exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue griefe. For the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding hereof, being a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I will giue thee a like exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, let vs cal to mind the hiſtory of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> &amp; that great famin that cotinued
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:180713:46"/>for the ſpace of ſeuen yeares in Egypt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 41.</note> before which famine (as the holy Scripture faith) the abundance of corne in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeuen yeares before was ſo great, that it might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the ſands of the ſea and exceeded all meaſure, but after that theſe ſeuen yeares were ended, there followed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeuen yeares of ſo great barrenneſſe and dearth, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the firſt yeare of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all, the people of Egypt came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore king <hi>Pharao,</hi> crying out and ſaying: <hi>Giue vs ſomewhat to eate.</hi> The king ſent them to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who required of them all the mony they had, &amp; gaue them for the ſame corne ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for that yeare: when that was conſumed and ſpent, they returned the yeare following vnto <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſaying, Giue vs
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:180713:46"/>to eate: what, wilt thou ſuffer vs to die for hunger in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuce, becauſe wee haue no more money to giue thee? to whom he aunſwered: deliuer vnto me al your heards of cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, and for the ſame I will giue you corne in exchange, ſince you haue no more money left. After that they had deliuered vnto him all their cattell, and that their prouiſion was alſo ſpent, they came againe to him the next yeare, ſaying; now thou knoweſt my Lord that we haue no money, nor cattell to giue thee, and there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing elſe but onely our bodies and lands, how canſt thou ſuffer vs to die here for hunger in thy ſight, our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and lands, which are only left of all our ſubſtance are thine, buy vs as ſlaues for the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:180713:47"/>king, &amp; giue vs (if it be thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) corn to ſow the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lie not vntilled, &amp; deſolate, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are al dead that ſhold til &amp; inhabit it. By this meane came Ioſeph to buy al the land in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, for euery one ſould his poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s by reaſon of the great famine which they ſuffred: thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is the hiſtory. Now let vs take that out of it that ſerueth to out purpoſe, tell me then I beſeech thee, what a griefe was it vnto theſe miſerable me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of thoſe vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plentifull yeres paſt, &amp; ſaw we with how little money they might haue prouided corne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, yea, and haue layd v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo wherby to inrich the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelue during their liues, how iuſtly might they lament &amp; reprou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, ſaying, ô how vnfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tunate are we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> might ſo eaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:180713:47"/>haue prouided for this dearth, and would not, if we had not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in admoniſhed of this before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and, then perhaps our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gence might haue had ſome excuſe, but being thereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>duertiſed ſo long time before, &amp; ſeeing with al, what ſpeed &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iligence the kings purueyours made to gather together &amp; lay vp all the corne they could get, the which was ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to giue vs to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what we ought to haue done in that behalfe, &amp; yet for all this to be ſo ſlothfull, &amp; careles as we were, what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue? O how much worth wold that be to vs at this preſent which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we deſpiſed, &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned! what riches might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee now get with the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orne, which we did the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y caſt away? But (my good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rethren) all this is but as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:180713:48"/>dow compared with the truth That famine in Egypt endure only for ſeuen yeares, but thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in hel ſhal indure euerlaſtingly that found a remedy, though with great difficulty &amp; charge but for this, there ſhall neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny remedy be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; that might be redeemed with money an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cattell, but this can neuer be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with any maner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, this puniſhment can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be pardoned, this paine ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be exchanged, this ſenten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cannot be reuoked: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, thoſe men of Egypt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the ſeuen yeares we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ended, began to lift vp their heads, and to come out of their miſerie, but in hell whoſoeur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> once entreth to be puniſhed ſhall neuer know againe what reſt and eaſe meaneth. Now if they then notwithſtanding al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:180713:48"/>this were during that time ſo much afflicted and vexed, in how much worſe caſe ſhall he be that ſhall ſee himſelfe in hell fire ſo horribly tormented, and vexed, and that without all hope of remedie? O if thou kneweſt, and wouldeſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how euery one of them ſhall there ſtand tormenting, &amp; renting himſelfe, weeping, and wayling, and ſaying, ô miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and vnfortunate wretch that I am, what times, &amp; what oportunities haue I ſuffered to paſſe in vaine; a time there was, when with one ſup of cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I might haue purchaſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſelfe a Crowne of glory, wherefore did I not looke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me? how was I blinded with things preſent? how did I let paſſe thoſe fruitfull yeares of ſuch abundance, and did not
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:180713:49"/>enrich my ſelfe? yea if I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bene brought vp among in ſidels and pagans, and had be lecued that there had bene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but only to be bom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and die, then might I haue ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome kind of excuſe, and might haue ſaid that I knew not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> was forbidden me, but for ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> much as I haue liued amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtians, and was my ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one of them, and held in for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> article of my beleefe, that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hower ſhould come, when ſhould giue vpon account a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what order I had ſpent m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life: for ſo much alſo as it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> daily cried out vnto me, by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> continuall preaching and te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of religious perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aduertiſements many follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made preparation in tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; labored earneſtly for the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſouls health, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:180713:49"/>life alſo and example was a greater proofe of that which they ſpake: for ſo much I ſay as I made light of theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and preachings, &amp; perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my ſelfe very fondly, that heauen was prepared for me, though I tooke no paines for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> at al, what deſerue I that haue thus led my life? O ye infernall ſuries come and rent me in beeces, and deuour theſe my bowels, for ſo haue I iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerued: I haue deſerued to be hunger ſtarued for euer, ſeeing I would not prouide for my ſelfe, while I had time: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſerue not to reape, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> haue not ſowne, I am wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy to bee deſtitute fith I haue not layd vp in ſtore. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> deſerue that now my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ueſt ſhould bee dinied me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th when the poore made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:180713:50"/>vnto me, I refuſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> leaſe them: I haue deſerued ſigh and lament in vaine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> long as God ſhall bee God; haue deſerued that this wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhold gnaw my o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals for euer &amp; euer, by rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting vnto me the little ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure which I haue enioyed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the great felicity which I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> loſt, and how farre greater th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> was which I might haue gain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by forgoing that little which would not forgo. This is the immortall worme that ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> uer die, but ſhall lie there eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinglie gnawing at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> trailes of the wicked, which one of the moſt tirrible pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that can poſſiblie bee im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Section.</hi> 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thou wilt peraduenture b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a mazed (good Chriſtian bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) in reading ſo many kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:180713:50"/>of paines in hell, as hath bene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere deſcribed, and now thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt perſwaded that there can be added vnto this no more then hath bene ſayd, but ſurely the mighty of God wanteth not force to chaſtice his enmies more and more, for all the paines that we haue hitherto chearſed, as ſuch as do apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aine generallie to all the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but beſides theſe generall paines there be other particular paines, which each one of the damned ſhall there ſuffer in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerſe ſort, according to the qualitie of his ſinne, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this proportion,<note place="margin">The proud.</note> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aughtie and proude ſhal there be a baſed and brought low to their confuſion, the couetous ſhall bee driuen to miſerable neceſſity,<note place="margin">The coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous. The glutton.</note> the glutton ſhal rage with continuall hunger and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:180713:51"/>thirſt,<note place="margin">The Leche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note> the lecherous ſhall bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the very ſame flames which they themſelues haue enkin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and thoſe that haue al the life time liued diſſolutely an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hunted after their pleaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and paſtimes, ſhall liue the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in continuall lamentation an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſorrow.</p>
               <p>Now then if all this ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuredly come to paſſe, what m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is he that ſeeing all this ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely with the eyes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> faith, will not turne ouer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leaſe, and begin to prouide fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf againſt that time: who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is the iudgement of men not become? where be their with where is at the leaſt their ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> loue, which ſeeketh euermo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for his owne profit, &amp; is much afraid of any loſſe, what? may it be thought that men are be come beaſtes, that prouide on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:180713:51"/>for the time preſent &amp; neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ct time to come? or haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey peraduenture ſo dimmed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir eye-ſight, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not looke before them? Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en (ſayth Eſay) ô yea deaffe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd yee blind, open your eies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at you may ſee: who is blind but my ſeruant? and who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaffe but ye to whom I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt my meſſengers? and who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> blind but hee that ſuffereth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mſelfe to be ſould for a ſlaue? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hou that ſeeſt ſo many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings wilt thou not ſee this? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ou that haſt thine eares open, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ilt thou not giue eare here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto? if thou beleeue nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his, how art thou a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ian? and if thou beleeue it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd doſt not prouide for it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow canſt thou bee thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reaſonable man? <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otle</hi> faith, that this is the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:180713:52"/>difference betweene an opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion and imagination, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> imagination alone is not ſuf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient to cauſe a feare, but an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinion is: for if I do imagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that a houſe may fall vpon m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> it is not enough to make me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fraid, vnleſſe I beleeue or ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> an opinion that it will be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed: for then it is ſufficient make me afraid: and here commeth the feare that mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theres alwayes haue, by reaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the ſuſpition they concei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that their enemies doe lie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> waite for them. If then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinion and onely ſuſpition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> daunger, is able to cauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt valiant and couragious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feare, how is it that the ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taintie and beliefe of ſo man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſo great terrible miſeries which is farre more ſure then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny opinion or knowledge, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:180713:52"/>make thee to feare, if thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueſt that for this many yeres paſt thou haſt led a licentious and ſinfull life, and that at the laſt according to preſent iuſtice thou art condemned to theſe terrible torments of hell: I may alſo probablie coni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cture, that there is no other likelihood of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thy life to come the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt ſhewed hitherto after ſo many yeares paſt: how hapneth it, that running head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long forwards into ſo manifeſt a danger, thou art nothing at all afraid, eſpecially conſidering the ſinfull ſtate wherein thou liueſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and the horrible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aines and torments, which do attend for thee, and the time that thou haſt loſt, and the endleſſe repentance which thou ſhalt haue therefore in the moſt horrible torments of hell? aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:180713:53"/>it paſſeth all common ſence, to conſider that there ſhould bee ſuch wilfull groſſe blindneſſe in men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Glorie of the Bleſſed Saints in Heauen. Chap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO the ende there might want nothing to ſtirre vp our minds vnto vertue, after the paines which almightie God threatneth vnto the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, he doth alſo ſet before vs the reward of the good, which is, that glorie, and that euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, which the bleſſed Saints doe enioy in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen: whereby he doth very mightily allure vs to the loue of the ſame, but what manner of thing this reward, &amp;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:180713:53"/>what this life is, there is no tongue, neither of Angels nor yet of men, that is ſufficient to expreſſe it, howbeit that we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may haue ſome kind of ſauour and knowledge thereof, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to rehearſe here euerie word, what Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſay th in one of his medetati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſpeaking of this life. O life (ſayth hee) prepared by almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty God for his friends, a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed life, a ſecure life, a quiet life, a bewtifull life, a cleane life, a chaſt life, a holy life, a life that knoweth no death, a life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſadneſſe, without labour, without griefe, without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, without corruption, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, without varietie, without alteration, a life reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all bewtie and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, where there is neither e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:180713:54"/>that can offend, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light that can annoy, where loue is perfect, and no feare a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all: where the day is euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and the ſpirit of al is one where almighty God is ſeene face to face, who is the onely meate whereupon they ſeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without any lothſomneſſe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> delighteth me to conſider thy brightneſſe, and thy treaſure do delight my longing heart the more I conſider thee, the more I am ſtriken in loue with thee: the great deſire I haue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee, doth wonderfully deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me, &amp; no leſſe pleaſure is it vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to me to keepe thee in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. O life moſt happy! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kingdome truely bleſſed wherein there is no death, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> end, neither yet ſucceſſion e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time, where the day continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:180713:54"/>euermore without night, knoweth not any mutation: where the victorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour being ioyned with the euerlaſting companies of Angels, and hauing his head Crowned with a garland of glorie, ſinging vnto almighty God one of the ſongs of Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: O happie, yea and moſt happie ſhould my ſoule bee, if when the race of this my pilgrimage is ended, I might be worthy to ſee thy glory, thy bleſſedneſſe, thy beauty, the walles and gates of thy Citty, thy ſtreetes, thy lodgings, and thy noble Citizens, and thine omnipotent king in his moſt glorious Maieſtie: the ſtones of thy walles are precious, thy gates are adorned with bright pearles, thy ſtreetes are of very fine excellent gold, in which
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:180713:55"/>there neuer faile perpetuall praiſes, thy houſes are paued with rich ſtones, wrought throughout with Saphires, and couered aboue with maſſie gold: where none entreth in that is not cleane, neither doth doth any abide there that is defiled: faire and bewtifull in thy delights art thou ô Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: none of thoſe things are ſuffered in thee, that are ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red here: there is great diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie betweene thy things, and the things we doe continually ſee in this miſerable life: in thee is neuer ſeene neither darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe nor night, neither yet any change of time, the light that ſhineth in thee commeth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes, nor of the moone, nor yet of the bright gliſtring ſtarres, but God that procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of God, and the light that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:180713:55"/>commeth of light is he that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth clearneſſe vnto thee, euen the very king of kings himſelfe keepeth continual reſidence in the midſt of thee, compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with his officers, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: there do Angels in their order ſing a moſt ſweete, and melodious harmonie, there is celebrated a perpetuall ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and feaſt, with euery one of them that commeth thither after his departure out of this pilgrima ge, there be the orders of Prophets, there is the famous company of the Apoſtles, there is the inuincible army of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,<note place="margin">The bleſſ companie heauen.</note> there are the true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect religious perſons, there are the holy virgins which haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome both the pleaſure of the world, and the frailtie of their owne nature, there are the young men, and yong wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:180713:56"/>more auncient in vertue then in yeares: there are the ſheepe, and little lambes, that haue eſcaped from the wolfe, and from the deceiptfull ſnares of this life, and there doe now keepe a perpetuall feaſt each one in his place all alike in ioy, though differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in degree; there charity raigneth in her full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, for vnto them God is all in all, whom they behold without ende, in whoſe loue they will be al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, whom they alwayes loue and in louing doe praiſe, and in prayſing doe loue, and all their exerciſes conſiſt in praiſes, without wearineſſe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trauell. O happie were I yea and very happie indeede, if what time I ſhall be looſed out of the priſon of this wretched bodie, I might bee
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:180713:56"/>thought worthy to heare thoſe ſongs of that heauenly melody, ſong in the praiſe of the euer laſting king by all the Citizens of that ſo noble city: happie were I, and very happie, if I might obtaine a roome among the chaplaines of that chappell, and waite for my turne to ſing praiſes to my God: if I might be neere to my King, my God, my Lord, and ſee him in his glory, euen as he promiſed me, when he ſayd: O father this is my laſt determinate wil, that all thoſe that thou haſt giuen vnto me, may be with me, and ſee the glory which I had with thee before the world was created: hitherto are the words of Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now tell me (good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an reader) what a day ſhall that be, that ſhall ſhine in thy
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:180713:57"/>houſe (if thou leade thy life in the feare of God) when after the courſe of this pilgrimage, thou ſhalt paſſe from death te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> immortalitie, &amp; in that paſſage when others ſhall beginne to feare, thou ſhalt beginne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, and lift vp thy head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the day of thy deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is at hand. Come foorth a little (ſayth Saint Ierome) out of the priſon of this body, and when thou art before the gate of the Tabernacle, ſet before thine eies the reward thou ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt for: tel me, what a day ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that be, when the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with all his Saints, ſhall come and meete thee in the way, ſaying vnto thee, <hi>Ariſe, &amp; make haſt, ô my beloued, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and my turtle-doue, for now the winter is paſt, and the tempeſtuous waters are ceaſed,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:180713:57"/>and flowers begin to appeare in our land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How great ioy ſhall thy ſoule then receiue, when it ſhall be at that time preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of the moſt bleſſed Trinity, by the hands of the holy Angels? how clearely ſhalt thou vnderſtand the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and excellency of vertue; there the obedient man ſhall talke of victories, there vertue ſhall receiue herreward, and the good ſhall be honored ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deſert: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, what a pleaſure will it be vnto thee, when thou ſhalt ſee thy ſelfe to be in that ſure ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, when thou ſhalt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the tempeſtes wherein thou haſt beene toſſed, the ſtraights through which thou haſtpaſſed, and the daungers
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:180713:58"/>which thou haſt paſſed, and the daungers of theeues, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped this is the place, where they ſhall ſing the ſong of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, which ſayth, <hi>Had it not bene that the Lord had bene my helper, it could not bee but that my ſoule had gone to hell.</hi> And how it hath pleaſed almightie God, that among ſuch a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of damned perſons, thou ſhouldeſt be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his elect, and one of thoſe to whom hee would graunt ſuch exceeding great felicitie, and glorie. Beſides all this, what a goodly ſight ſhall it be to behold the feaſtes, and triumphes, which they daily celebrate with their new brethren, who hauing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the world, and finiſhed
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:180713:58"/>the courſe of their pilgrimage, do enter in there to be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them. O what a ioy will it be to ſee thoſe ſeates fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp, and that Citie builded, and the walles of that noble <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> repaired again: with what cheerefull imbracings ſhall the whole Court of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen intertaine them, beholding them when they come loden with the ſpoiles of the vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed enemie? There ſhall thoſe valiant men and women en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with triumph, which haue together with the world, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the weakeneſſe of their owne frayle nature: there ſhall the innocent virgins en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which haue ſuffered martyrdome for Chriſts ſake, with double triumph ouer the fleſh, and the worlde,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:180713:59"/>adorned alſo with garlands o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lillies, and roſes vpon their heads: there ſhall alſo ente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dayly manie young men and children, which haue vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the tenderneſſe of their yong yeares with diſcretion &amp; vertue, and ſhall receiue their rewarde: ô how ſweete and ſauerie ſhall the fruit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vertue then be, although for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time before, her rootes ſeeme verie bitter: ſweet is the cold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euening after the hote ſunny day: ſweet is the fountaine to the wearie traueller: ſweet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſt and ſleepe to the tired ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant: but much more ſweet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it to the Saints in heauen to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy peace after warre, ſecurity after perils, eternall reſt after their paines and trauels, for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are the wars at an end, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> need they no more to go all armed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:180713:59"/>on the right &amp; on the left ſide. The children of Iſraell went forth armed towards the land of promiſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.</note> but after that the land was conquered, they laid downe their ſpeares, &amp; caſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their armour, forgetting al feare and turmoyle of warre: each one vnder the ſhadow of his pauilion and harbour, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed the fruit of their ſweet peace. Now may the eyes ſleep there, that haue bene wearied with continuall watching,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> now may the watching Prophet come downe from his ſtanding that did watch and fixe his feet vpon the place of the centinell. There is no more feare of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion by the terrible armies of the bloudy enemie, there is no place for the ſuttle craſts of the lurking viper, there cannot arriue the deadly ſight of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:180713:60"/>venimous Baſiliske, neither yet ſhall the hiſſing of the ancien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſerpent be heard there, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſoft breathing aire of the holy Ghoſt, wherein is behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the glorie of Almighty God: this is the region of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; place of ſecuritie, ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue all the elements, whither the cloudes and ſtormie windes of the dark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aire cannot come. O wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> glorious things haue been ſpoken of thee, ô Citie of God Bleſſed are they (ſaith holy <hi>Tobias)</hi> that loue thee, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy thy peace. O my ſoule praiſe the Lord, for he hath deliuered <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> his Citie from all her tribulations. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſhall I be, if the remnant o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my poſteritie might come to ſee the cleareneſſe of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Her gates ſhalbe wrough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:180713:60"/>with Saphires and Emeralds, and all the circuit of her walles ſhall be built with precious ſtones: her ſtreets ſhall be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ued with white and poliſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>marble, and in all parts of her territorie ſhall be ſong praiſes. O Ioyful cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, ôſweet glory! O bleſſed company! who ſhall be ſo fortunate and ſo happy as thoſe that are elected for thee? It ſeemeth a preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thee, and yet I will not liue without the deſire of thee: ô ye ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> ô race of men miſerably blinded and deceiued! ô ye ſcattered ſheep wandering out of the right way, if this be your ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cote, whither go ye backward? what meane you? why ſuffer you ſuch an excellent benefite to be wilfully loſt, for not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo litle paine? If labour &amp;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:180713:61"/>trauell be requiſite hereu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> furely from henceforth I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſire that all the labor &amp; paine of the world were layd vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me: let all ſorrowes po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> downe vpon me as thicke i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haile, let diſeaſes vexe me, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tribulations afflict me, let o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſecute me, let another d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quiet me, let all creatures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the world conſpire againſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let me be made a laughing ſtocke to all men, and a ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to the world: yea, and let m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life be wholly conſumed wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> griefes &amp; my yeares with we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and lamentation, ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> after this life, I may reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe in the day of tribulation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and be thought meete to hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a place among the bleſſed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which are adorned ao<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beautified with ſuch ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble glorie in the kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:180713:61"/>heauen.</p>
               <p>Now then, ô thou fooliſh louer of this miſerable world, go thy way, ſeeke as long as thou wilt for honors and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, build ſumptuous hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and pallaces, purchaſe lands &amp; poſſeſſions, enlarge thy ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories and dominions, yea, &amp; command, if thou wilt, whole empires and worlds, yet ſhalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou neuer be ſo great as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſt of all the ſeruants of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God: who ſhal receiue that treaſure which this world cannot giue, and ſhall enioy that felicitie which ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for euermore; thou with thy pompe and riches ſhalt keepe companie with the rich Glutton, buried in the deepe pit of hell: but the deuout ſpirituall man ſhall be caried vp by the holy Angels with
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:180713:62"/>poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> into <hi>Abr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> boſome.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 13.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the benefits which the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promiſeth to giue in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſuch as liue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſt &amp; g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life. Chap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PEradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture thou wilt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay, that all theſe things b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed, be rewards, puniſhments that are promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> onely for the life to come, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that thou deſireſt to ſee ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this preſent life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our minds are wont <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be much moued with the ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of things preſent. Well, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thee herein, we will like wiſe giue thee here thy han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> full, euen of that thou doeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> earneſtly deſire: for althoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:180713:62"/>the Lord do reſerue the beſt wine, and the moſt delicate diſhes vntill the end of the banket, yet he ſuffereth not his friends to be vtterly deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute of meate and drinke in this tedious voyage: for he knoweth verie well that they could not otherwiſe hold out in their iourney: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he ſaid vnto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> Feare not <hi>Abraham,</hi> for I am thy defender, and thy reward ſhall be exceeding great. By theſe words he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed two things: the one for the time preſent, that was, to be his ſauegard and defence in all ſuch things as might happen in this life: and the other for the time to come: and that is the reward of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which is reſerued for the next life. But how great
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:180713:63"/>the firſt promiſe is, and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many kinds of benefits, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, are therein included, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man is able to vnderſtand, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only he that hath with gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diligence read the holy Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, wherein no one thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more often rehearſed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forth, then the greatneſſe the fauours, benefites, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges which Almighty God promiſeth to his friends in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life. Hearken what <hi>Salom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> faith in his <hi>Trouerbes</hi> as to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this matter: Bleſſed that man that findeth wiſdom for it is better to haue it, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all the treaſures of ſiluer an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gold, be they neuer ſo preciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and excellent, and it is mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worth then all the riches of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> world, and whatſoeuer man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart is able to deſire, is not comparable vnto it. The le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:180713:63"/>of dayes are at her right hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd riches, &amp; glorie at her left. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er wayes are pleaſant, &amp; her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſages are quiet. She is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of life to al thoſe that haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tained her: and he that ſhall haue her in continuall poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all be bleſſed. Keepe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re, O my ſonne, the lawes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mightie God, and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ls, for they ſhall be as life to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y ſoule, and ſweetneſſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y taſte, then ſhalt thou walke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fely in thy wayes, &amp; thy feet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all not find any ſtumbling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ockes: if thou ſleepe, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alt haue no cauſe to feare, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thou take thy reſt, thy ſleepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all be quiet.</p>
               <p>Now this is (good Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>other) the ſweetneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uietneſſe of the way of the Godly, but the wayes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icked are farre different, as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:180713:64"/>the holie Scriptures do ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto vs: the paths and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the wicked (faith <hi>Ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtieus</hi>) are full of bramb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and at the end of their iou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hell, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> neſie and paine. Doeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thinke it then a good exth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to forſake the wayes of mightie God, for the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the world, ſith there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> great difference betweene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one and the ether, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the end of the way, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in all the ſteppes of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what madneſſe can be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then to chuſe rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> one torment to gaine anot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with one reſt to gaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ther reſt? And that thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> more clearely perceiue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cellencie of this leſt, and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a number of benefits are p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently incident thereunto
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:180713:64"/>beſeech thee hearken attentiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what euen Almightic God himſelfe hath promiſed by his Prophet Eſay, to the obſeruers of his Law, in a maner in theſe wordes, as diuerſe interpreters do expound them: when thou ſhalt do (faith he) ſuch &amp; ſuch things, which I haue comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee to do, then ſhal forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with appeare vnto thee, the dawning of the cleare day (that is the Sunne of iuſtice) which ſhal driue away all thine errors and miſeries, &amp; then ſhalt thou beginne to enioy true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſaluation, and all thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſinnes ſhall be blotted out of Gods remembraunce, and the glorie of the Lord ſhall compaſſe thee round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout: then ſhalt thou call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the name of the Lord, and he will ſurely heare thee, thou
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:180713:65"/>ſhalt call, and he will ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am here preſent and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to graunt thee whatſoeue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou ſhalt haue neede of: the in the midſt of the darknes, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations and vexations of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> life, the light of Gods fauour ſhal ſhine vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, which ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> comfort thee, and thy darkne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be as the noone day, (for the Lord wil ſo ordain, that the very calamities, &amp; withall, eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the very falls of thy ſinnes paſt ſhall be an occaſion vnto thee of thy greater felicitie) &amp; he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> giue thee alwayes true peace and quietneſſe in thy ſoule, and in the time of famine &amp; dearth he will ſende thee plentie and aboundance: and thy boner ſhal be deliuered from death, and from the euerlaſting fires and thou ſhalt be like a garden of pleaſure, and like a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:180713:65"/>of water that neuer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth running: of thee will hee make a building, (which laye for many yeares before deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late) in ſuch ſort that it ſhall ſtande ſtedfaſtly, and endure with ſure foundations from ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to generations. And if thou ſhalt take pains in ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying my Saboths, not in ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them in leude exerciſes, nor yet in fulfilling thy owne will againſt mine, but ſhalt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue withal diligence and care all ſuch things as I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded thee this day, then ſhalt thou take delight in the Lord (whoſe delights excell all the delights in the world) and I will lift thee vp aboue the heights of the earth, that is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a moſt happie ſtate of life, whereunto all the treaſures of fortune or of humaine nature
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:180713:66"/>can not reach. Finally, I will giue thee afterwardes plentie and abundance of that precious inheritance, which I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed vnto Iacob thy father which is the felicitie of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it. All theſe in a manner, bee the wordes of Almightie God by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay.</p>
               <p>Nowe theſe are the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, which Almightie God hath promiſed to his ſeruaunts: and albeit ſome of them be for the time to come, yet are ſome of them to bee preſently recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this life, as that newe light and ſhining from heauen, that ſacietie and aboundance of all good things: and aſſured confidence &amp; truſt in Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God: that deuine aſſiſtance in all our prayers and petition:
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:180713:66"/>made vnto him: that peace and tranquillitie of conſcience, that protection and prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Almightie God, that garden of delights (which is the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and beautie of grace) that fountaine which neuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth water, (which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion &amp; ſufficiencie of things.) Thus heauenly delights do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel all the delights of the world, and that eleuation of ſpirite, whereunto no ſtrength or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of nature is able to aſpire. All theſe are the gracious gifts and fauours which Almightie God hath promiſed to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt in this life. They all are his workes of his mercie, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes of his grace, teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of his loue, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which hee of his fatherly prouidence ſheweth towardes
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:180713:67"/>them, vppon euery one of which there is ſo much to be ſayd, that the breuity of this volume will not ſuffer me to treate particularly of euery point: but to be ſhort, all theſe benefits doe the godly enioy, both in this preſent life, and in the life to come, &amp; of all theſe are the vngodly depriued, both in the one life, and in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Whereby thou maiſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceiue, what difference there is betweene the one ſon and the other, ſeeing the one is ſo rich, and the other ſo poore, and needy: for if thou ponder well all theſe words before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and do likewiſe conſider the ſtate and conditious both of the good and the wicked, thou ſhalt find, that the one ſort are in the fauour of Almighty God, and the other in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:180713:67"/>the one be his friends,<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſtate of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> good &amp; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ked.</note> and the other his enemies; the one be in light, and the other be in darkneſſe; the one do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the company of Angels, &amp; the other the filthy pleaſures and delights of finne; the one are truely free, and Lords ouer themſelues, and the other are become bond-ſlaues vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and vnto their luſtes and appetites; the one are ioyfull with the witneſſe of a good conſcience, and the other (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they bee vtterly blinded) are continually bitten with the worme of conſcience euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more gnawing one them; the one in tribulations ſtand ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly in their proper place, and the other like light chaffe are carried vp &amp; downe with euery blaſt of wind; the one ſtand ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure &amp; firme with the anker of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:180713:68"/>hope, and the other are vnſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and euermore yeelding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the aſſaults of fortune: the prayers of the one are accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and liking vnto God, and the prayers of the other are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred and accurſed: the death of the one is quiet, peaceable, &amp; precious in the ſight of God, the death of the other is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, painefull, and troubled with a thouſand frights and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. To conclude, the one liue like childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and defence of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, and ſleepe ſweetly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadow of his paſtorall prouidence, and the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing excluded from this kinde of prouidence, wander abroade like ſtraied ſheep without their ſhepeheard and maiſter, lying wide open to all the perils, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and aſſaults of the world.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:180713:68"/>Now then (my deare brother) if a vertuous life be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with all theſe benefites, tell me I pray thee of good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, what is the cauſe ſhall withdraw thee, and perſwade thee not to embrace ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious treaſure? what art thou able to alleage for excuſe of thy great negligence? to ſay, that this is not true, it can not bee admitted, for ſo much as thou ſeeſt, that all is grounded vppon the word of God, and the teſtimonies of his holie Scriptures: and to ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 69.</note> that theſe are but ſmall benefites, thou canſt not, for ſo much as they doe exceede (as we haue before declared) all that mans heart can deſire. To ſay, that thou art an enemie vnto thy ſelfe, and that thou dooeſt not defire theſe benefites,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:180713:69"/>this cannot be ſayd, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that man is euen naturally a friend to himſelfe, and the will of man hath euer an eye to his owne benefit, which is the very obiect, or marke that his deſire ſhooteth at: to ſay that thou haſt no vnderſtanding or taſt of theſe benefits, it will not ſerue to diſcharge thine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, for ſo much as thou haſt the faith and beliefe, though thou haſt not the taſt, for the taſt is loſt through ſin, but not the faith;<note place="margin">Faith is a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aine wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſe, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſſes and experiences <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the world.</note> and the faith is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe more certaine, more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and better to bee truſted, then all other experiences, and witneſſes in the world: why doſt thou not then diſcredit all other witneſſes, with this one aſſured teſtimony? why doſt thou not rather giue credit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to faith, than to thine owne
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:180713:69"/>opinion and iudgement? O that thou wouldeſt make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute determination to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy ſelfe into the hands of Almighty God, and to put thy whole truſt aſſuredly in him: how ſoone ſhouldeſt thou ſee all theſe prophecies fulfilled in thee? then ſhouldeſt thou ſee the excellency of theſe deuine treaſures, then ſhouldeſt thou ſee how ſtarke blind the louers of this world are, that ſeeke not after this high treaſure. To be ſhort, then ſhouldeſt thou ſee vpon what good ground our Sauiour inuiteth vs to this kind of life: ſaying: <hi>Come vnto me all ye that trauell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and are loden, and I will refreſh you: take my yoke vpon you, and you ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules; for my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oke is ſweete, and my
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:180713:70"/>burthen is light.</hi> Almightie God is no deceiuer, not falſe promiſer, neither yet is hee a great boaſter of ſuch things as he promiſeth, why doeſt thou then ſhrinke backe! why doeſt thou refuſe peace and quietneſſe? why doeſt thou deſpiſe the gentle offers and ſweete callings of thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors? how dareſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe and baniſh away vertue from thee, which hath ſuch prerogatiues and priuiledges as theſe be, and withall confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſigned euen with the hand of Almightie God. The Queene of Saba heard far leſſe things thee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>an.</hi> 9.</note> &amp; yet ſhe trauelled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt partes of the earth to trie the truth of thoſe things wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe had heard, &amp; why doeſt not thou then hauing ſuch notable,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:180713:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>yea and ſo certaine newes of vertue, aduenture to take a little paines to trie the truth and ſequele thereof? O my deere Chriſtian brother, put thy truſt in Almighty God, and in his word, and commit thy ſelfe boldly without all feare into his armes, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace from thy handes triflings knots, that haue hitherto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued thee, and thou ſhalt finde that the deedes of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, doe farre excell her fame, and that all which is ſpoken in praiſe of her is nothing, in compariſon of that which ſhe is in deed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:180713:71"/>
               <head>That a man ought not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre his repentance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion vnto God from day to day, conſidering that hee hath ſo many debts to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, by reaſon of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences committed in his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life paſt. Chap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw then if on the one ſide there be ſo many &amp; ſo great reſpects that do bind vs to change our ſinfull life, and on the other ſide, wee haue not any ſufficient excuſe why we ſhould not make this exchange, I beſeech thee tell me, how long time wilt thou tarrie vntill thou fullie reſolue to do it; turne thine eyes (ô my Chriſtian brother) and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:180713:71"/>looke backe a little vppon thy life paſt, and conſider that at this preſent of what age ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou be, it is high time, or rather the time is well neere paſt to begin to diſcharge ſome part of thine old debts; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that thou who art a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, regenerated in the holy water of Baptiſme, who doeſt acknowledge Almighty God for thy father, conſider I ſay, that all this notwithſtanding thou haſt liued euen as looſely, and diſſolutely, as thou hadſt bene a meere infidell, that had neuer any knowledge of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God: and if thou deny this, then tell me what kind of ſinne is there that thou haſt not committed, what tree is there forbidden, that thou haſt not beholden with thine eyes? what greene meddow is there
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:180713:72"/>in which thou haſt not (at the leaſt with deſire) feaſted thy le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous luſtes? what thing hath bene ſet before thine eyes, that thou haſt not wantonly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? what appetite haſt thou left vnexecuted, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that thou didſt beleeue in Almighty God, and that thou wert a Chriſtian? what woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou haue done more, if thou haddeſt not had any faith at all, if thou haddeſt not loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for any other life, if thou haddeſt not feared the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day of iudgement? What hath all thy former life bene, but a webbe of ſinnes, a ſinke of vices, a way full of bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and thornes, and a fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde diſobedience of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, with whom thou haſt hitherto liued, but onely with thine appetite,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:180713:72"/>with thy fleſh, with thy pride, and with thy goodes, and riches of this tranſitory world? theſe haue beene thy gods, theſe haue bene thine Idols, whom thou haſt ſerued, whoſe lawes thou haſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obeyed: make thine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts with Almighty God, with his lawes, with his odedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and peraduenture thou ſhalt find that thou haſt eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him no more then if hee had bene a God of ſtraw, for it is certaine, that there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtians, which beleeuing that there is a God, are induced to ſinne with ſuch facility, as though they did beleeue that there were no God at al: &amp; do offend no whit leſſe, though they beleeue that there is a God, then they would doe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:180713:73"/>they beleeued that there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> none at all. What greater in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, what greater deſpite c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> there bee done, then thus to contemne his deuine maieſty. Finally, thou beleeuing all ſuch things, haſt notwithſtanding ſo led thy life, as if thou we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perſwaded that the beliefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Chriſtians were the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reſt fables or lies in the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> world.</p>
               <p>And if the multitude of thy ſinnes paſt, and the facility thou haſt vſed in committing of them, do not make thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, why doſt thou not feare at the leaſt the Maieſty &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency of him, againſt whom thouhaſt ſinned? Life vp thine eyes, and conſider the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite greatneſſe and omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of the Lord, whom the powers of heauen doe adore,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:180713:73"/>before whoſe Maieſtie the whole compaſſe of the wide world lyeth proſtrate, in whoſe preſence all things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted are no more then chaſſe, carried away with the wind: conſider alſo with thy ſelfe, how vnſeemely it is, that ſuch a vile worme as thou art, ſhould haue audacitie ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times to offend &amp; prouoke the wrath of ſo great a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
               <p>Conſider the wonderfull &amp; moſt terrible ſeueritie of his iuſtice,<note place="margin">The terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeuere iuſtice of almightie God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinners.</note> and what horrible pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments hee hath vſed from time to time in the world, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, and that not onely againſt particular perſons but alſo vppon Cities, Nations, Kingdomes, and Prouinces: yea vpon the vniuerſall world, and not only in earth, but alſo
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:180713:74"/>in heauen, not only vpon ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers and ſinners, but euen vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his owne moſt innoce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, our ſweete Sauiour Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, when he tooke vppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him to ſatisfie for the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that they owed. And if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeuerity was vſed vppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> innocent &amp; greene wood, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the ſinnes of others, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then will he do vpon drie an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> withered wood, and againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe that are loden with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> owne ſinnes? Now what thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can be thought more vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, then that ſuch a vil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wretched weake dwarfe a thou,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 13. <hi>verſe.</hi> 43.</note> ſhouldeſt be ſo ſawcie and mallaparte, as to mocke with ſo mighty a Lord, whoſe hand is ſo heauie, that in caſe hee ſhould ſtricke, but euen one ſtroke vppon thee, hee would at
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:180713:74"/>one blow driue thee downe head-long into the deepe and bottomleſſe pitte of hell; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here to be tormented for euer by the diuels and his Angles, without all hope of reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</p>
               <p>Conſider likewiſe the great patience of this our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Lord,<note place="margin">The great pacience of Almighty God.</note> who hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected thy repentaunce ſo long, euen from the time that thou didſt firſt offend him, and thinke that if after ſo great patience, and long tarrying for thee, thou ſhalt ſtill continue thy lewde and ſinfull life, abuſing thus his mercie, and not ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to prouoke him to further indignation and wrath, he will then bend his bow, and ſhake his ſworde, and raine downe
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:180713:75"/>vpon thee, euen very ſharp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> arrowes of euerlaſting death.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo the profoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his iudgements,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundneſſe of the deepe iudgements of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God.</note> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of we reade and ſee dayly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great wonders: we ſee ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> king <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe, after be ſo great wiſedome, and afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe three thouſand parable and moſt profound miſterie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vttered by him in his book called <hi>Cantica Canticoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was ſorſaken of almighty God and fuffered to fall downe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 11.</note> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> adore Idols: wee ſee day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many ſtarres fall downe from heauen to the earth, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſerable falles,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ato.</hi> 2.</note> and to wallo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelues in the durt, and to cate the meate of ſwine, which ſate before at Gods table, and were fed with the very brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Angels. If then the iuſt and righteous for ſome ſecrete
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:180713:75"/>pride, or negligence, or elſe for ſome ingratitude of theirs, be thus iuſtly forſaken of almighty God, after they haue beſtowed ſo many yeares in his ſeruice, what mayſt thou looke for, that haſt done nothing elſe all thy life time, but onely heaped vp ſinnes vpon ſinnes, and haſt thereby offended Almighty God, moſt grieuouſly.</p>
               <p>Now if thou haſt liued after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his ſort, were it not reaſon that thou ſhouldeſt now at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ength giue ouer, and ceaſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſinne vpon ſinne, and debt vpon debt, and begin to pacifie the wrath of almighty god, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o diſburthen thy ſinfull ſoule: were it meete that that time which thou haſt hitherto giuen to the world, to the fleſh, and to the diuell, ſhould ſuffice, and that thou ſhouldeſt beſtow
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:180713:76"/>ſome litle time of that which remaineth to ſerue him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath giuen vnto thee all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thou haſt? were it not a po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of wiſedome after ſo long time and ſo many great iniuries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feare the moſt terrible iuſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Almighty God, who th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more patiently hee ſuffere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinners, the more doth hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> terward puniſh them wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greater ſeuerity and iuſtio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were it not meete for thee feare thy long continuance many yeares in ſinne, and in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſpleaſure of almighty God procuring thereby againſt the ſuch amighty aduerſary as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is, and prouoke him of a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull louing father, to be com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a ſeuere terrible judge and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nemy? were it not meete to feare, leaſt that the force of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cuſtome may in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:180713:76"/>of come be turned into na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that thy long vicious vſuall maner of committing of ſinne, may make of a vice a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, or litle leſſe? why art thou not afrayd leſt by litle &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litle thou maiſt caſt thy felſe downe headlong into the deep pit of a reprobate ſence,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into after that a man is once falle, he neuer maketh account of any ſinne, be it neuer ſo great.</p>
               <p>The Patriarke <hi>Iacob</hi> ſayd vnto <hi>Laban</hi> his father in law: Theſe fourteene yeares haue I ſerued thee, &amp; looked to thine affaires, now it is time, that I ſhould looke to mine owne, &amp; begin to attend vnto the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of mine owne houſhold. Wherfore if thou haſt likewiſe bestowed ſo many yeares, in the ſeruice of this world, and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:180713:77"/>of this frayle tranſitorie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were it not good reaſon, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou ſhouldeſt now be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make ſome prouiſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſaluation of thy ſoule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſon the euerlaſting life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come? There is nothing mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort, nor more tranſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, then the life of a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and therefore prouiding carefully as thou doeſt for ſuch things as bee neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for this life, which is ſo ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> why doeſt thou not likew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> prouide ſomewhat for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is to come, which ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endure for euer and euer?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The concluſion of all the premiſes. Chap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF now all this bee ſo, beſeech thee (ô my de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:180713:77"/>Chriſtian brother) euen for the bitter paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, to remember thy ſelfe, and to conſider that thou art a Chriſtian, and that thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueſt aſſuredly for a moſt vndoubted truth what thy faith inſtructeth: this faith telleth thee, thou haſt a iudge aboue, that ſeeth all the ſteps and motions of thy life; and that certainly there ſhall a day come, when hee will require an account of thee, euen of euery idle word: this faith tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth thee, that a man is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together at an end when hee dieth, but that after this tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life there remaineth another euerlaſting life, and that the ſoules dye not with the bodie, but that while the bodie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in the graue, vntill the generall day of iudgement,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:180713:78"/>the ſoule ſhall enter into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new countrey, and into a new world, where it ſhall haue ſuch habitation, and companie as the faith which it had in this life. This faith telleth thee alſo, that both the reward of vertue, and the puniſhment of vice, is a thing ſo wonderfull, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the world were full of bookes, and all creatures were writers, yet ſhould they all be wearied, and the world come to an end, before they ſhould end their deſcription, and make a perfect declaration, what is comprehended in each one of theſe points. This faith infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thee alſo, that the debts, and duties, which we owe vnto Almightie God, are ſo great, that albeit a man had ſo many liues, as there be ſands in the ſea, yet would they not ſuffice,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:180713:78"/>if they were all emploied in his ſeruice. And this faith like wiſe telleth thee, that vertue is ſuch an excellent treaſure, that all the treaſures of the world, and all that mans hart can deſire,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sap.</hi> 7.</note> are not to be compared vnto it.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if there be ſo many and great reſpectes that do inuite vs vnto vertue, how commeth it to paſſe, that there be ſo few louers and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the ſame? If men be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with gaine and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, what greater commoditie can there be, then life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting? if with feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what puniſhment can be greater, then euerlaſting horrible tormentes in hell fire, world without end? if with bondes of debtes, and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, what debtes are greater then thee, which we owe vnto
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:180713:79"/>Almightie God, aſwell for that hee is which hee is, as alſo for that which we haue receiued of him? If the feare of perils doe moue vs, what greater perill can there bee then death, the houre thereof being ſo vncertaine, and the account ſo ſtrait? If thou bee moued with peace, libertie, quietneſſe of minde, and with a pleaſant life (which are things that all the world deſireth) it is certaine, that all theſe are founde much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the life that is gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by vertue and reaſon, then in that life, that is tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the affections and paſſions of the minde, for ſo much as man is a reaſonable creature, and no beaſt. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in caſe thou accounteſt all this as not ſufficient to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:180713:79"/>moue thee thereunto, yet ſhall it not ſuffice thee to conſider, that Almightie God ſo abaſed him ſelfe for thy ſake, that he deſcended from heauen vnto the earth, and became man? and whereas hee created the world in fix daies, he beſtowed thirtie and three yeares about thy redemption, yea &amp; was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo content for the ſame to looſe his life: Almightie God dyed, that ſinne ſhould dye, &amp; yet for all this we doe endeuour that finnes might liue in our harts. Notwithſtading that Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God purpoſed to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the life of ſinne with his owne death, What ſhall I ſay more? aſſuredly of reaſons we haue ſhewed enough, and enough, if this matter were be to diſcuſſed by reaſon: for I ſay this, not onely in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding.
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:180713:80"/>Almightie God him ſelf, but whereſoeuer we turne our eyes, we ſhall finde that euery thing crieth out vnto vs, and calleth vpon vs to receiue this ſo excellent a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, for there is not a thing created in the world, (if we doe well conſider it) but doth inuite to the loue and ſeruice of our Lord and Sauiour: in ſo much that looke how many creatures there be in the world, ſo many prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers there are, ſo many books, ſo many voyces, and ſo many reaſons, which doe all call vs vnto Almightie God.</p>
               <p>And how is it poſſible then, that ſo many callings as theſe are, ſo many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and threatnings, ſhould not ſuffice to bring vs vnto him? What might Almightie
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:180713:80"/>God haue done more then he hath done, or promiſed more then hee hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed, or threatned more then hee hath threatned, to draw vs vnto him, and plucke vs from ſinne, and yet all this notwithſtanding, how commeth it to paſſe, that there is ſo great (I will not ſay arrogancie, but) be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of men, that doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue thoſe things to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, and yet bee not afrayd to continue all the dayes of their life in ſinne? yea to go to bed in ſinne, and to riſe vp againe in ſinne, and to embrew them ſelues in euery kinde of ſinne: and this is done in ſuch ſorte, ſo without feeling, ſo without feare, ſo without ſcruple of minde, and without
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:180713:81"/>breaking of one houres ſleepe as if al that they belieued we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dreames, and old wiues tales, and as if all that the holy euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes haue written, were meere vntruthes, &amp; ſtarke lies. Tell me now thou deſperare traitor, tell me I ſay thou fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand prepared to burne in thoſe euerlaſting and reuenging horrible fires of hell, what wouldſt thou haue done more then thou haſt done, in caſe thou haddeſt bene perſwaded that all were meere lyes, which thou haſt belieued: for although I ſee well, that for feare of externall puniſhment impoſed by the Princes law, thou haſt ſomewhat bridled thine appetites, yet can I not perceiue that for any feare of Almighty God thou
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:180713:81"/>haſt ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ained thy will in any one thing: neither from carnall pleaſures, nor from takinge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of thine enemies, nor from backbiting and ſlaunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy neighbours, nor yet from fulfilling thine inordinate and filthie luſtes and deſires, in caſe thine ability ſerued ther unto, tell me thou blind groſſe buzzard, and worſe then fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke fellow, what ſayth thy worme of conſcience vnto thee, whiles thou art in ſuch a fond ſecurity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, continuing in ſuch a careleſſe and diſſolue wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked life as thou doeſt, where is now become the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, iudgement, and reaſon, which thou haſt of a man? why art thou not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of ſo horrible, ſo certaine,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:180713:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:180713:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:180713:83"/>and ſo aſſured perils and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: if there were a diſh of meate ſet before thee, and ſome man (albeit he were a lier) ſhould ſay vnto thee that there were poyſon in that diſh, tell me, dareſt thou once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to ſtretch foorth thy hand to take a taſt thereof, though the meate were neuer ſo ſauery and delicate, and hee neuer ſo great a lier that ſhold beare thee thus in hand? If the Prophets, if the Apoſtles, if the Euangeliſtes, yea if Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God himſelfe doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one vnto thee, and ſay. Take heede miſerable man for deal is in that kind of meate, and death lyeth lurking in that glintenous morſell, which the diuell hath ſet before thee, how dareſt thou reach for euer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſting death with thy owne
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:180713:83"/>hands, &amp; drinke thine one dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: to what vſe putteſt thou in this meane while thy wits, thy iudgements, and thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4.</note> and reaſon, which thou haſt of a man, where is their light, where is their force, ſith that none of them: doe bridle thee any whit from thy common vſe of vices? O thou wretched and madde careleſſe ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe, bewitched by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, adiudged to euerlaſting darheneſſe, both in ward and outward, and ſo goeſt on from one darkeneſſe to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou are blind to ſee thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> miſery, inſenſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſland thy perdition, and harder then any adamant to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amer of Gods word. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>houſand times moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thou art, worthier to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with none other
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:180713:84"/>then with thoſe where with thy da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation was lamented: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was ſaid: O that thou kneweſt this day the peace, quietneſſe, and treaſures, which Almighty God offereth vnto thee, and do now lie hidden from thine eyes: O miſeraable is the day of thy natiuity, &amp; much more miſerable the day of thy death, for ſo much as that ſhall be the beginning of thy euerlaſting damnation:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.</note> ô how much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had it bene for thee neuer to haue bin borne,<note place="margin">The wicked Chriſtians ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in hell more grieuouſly for their wicked liues more then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>els.</note> if thou ſhall be damned in the moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vible torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of he fire for euer &amp; euer? How much better had it bene for thee neuer to haue beene baptized, if throughthe abuſing thereof by thy wicked life, thy damnation ſhal be ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the greater: for if the light of reaſon onely ſufficeth to make
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:180713:84"/>the heathen Philoſophers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, becauſe they know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God in ſome degree, did not glorifie him, nor ſerue him (as the Apoſtle ſayth) how much leſſe ſhall he be excuſed, that hath receiued the light of faith, and the water of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and doth often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the repreſentation of the Lords body, and euery day heareth his word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1</note> if he doe nothing more then theſe pagan Philoſophers haue done?</p>
               <p>Now what other thing may we inferre of the premiſes, but briefely to conclude, that there is none other vnderſtanding, none other wiſedome, none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther counſell in the worlde, but that ſetting aſide al the impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; comberſome dangerous
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:180713:85"/>wayes of this life, we ſolow on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that true and certaine way, whereby true peace and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life is obtained? hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we are called by reaſon, by wiſedome, by lawe, by heauen, by earth, by hell, and by the life, death, iuſtice, and mercie of Almightie God. Hereunto we are alſo inuited very notably by the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.</note> ſpeaking by the mouth of Eccleſiaſticus in this wiſe: My ſonne bearken to inſtruction, euen from the firſt yeares of thy youth, and in thy latter daies thou ſhalt enjoy the ſweete fruite of wiſedome: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch vnto it as one that plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſoweth, and with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence expect the fruitfull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe which it ſhall yeeld vnto thee. The paines that thou ſhall take, ſhall be but little, and the benefits that thou ſhalt quickly
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:180713:85"/>enioy, ſhall be great. May ſonne hearken to my words, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect not my counſell which I ſhall giue, put thy feet willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyinto her fetters, and thy necke into her chaines, bowe downe thy ſhoulders and carry her vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, and be not diſpleaſed with her bonds, approch neere vnto her with all thy heart, and follow her wayes with all thy ſtrength, ſeeke for her with all diligence, and ſhee will diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer her ſelfe vnto thee, and after that thou haſt found her neuer forſake her, for by her ſhalt thou findreſt in thy latter daies; and that which before ſeemed painefull, will afterwardes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come pleaſant vnto thee, and her fetters ſhalbe a defence of thy ſtrength, and foundation of vertue, and her chaine ſhall be arobe of glorie, for in her is the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:180713:86"/>very beauty of life, &amp; her both are the very bonds of health Hitherto are the words of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus, wherby thou maiſt in ſome degree vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, how great the beauty, the delight, the liberty, and riches of true wiſedome are, which is vertue it felſe, and the knowledge of Almighty God, whereof we do intreate. But iſ al this be not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to mollifie thy heart, lift vp thine eyes, &amp; fixe thy mind not vppon the water of the world, which vaniſh away, but vppon the Lord who died for our ſins: there ſtan deth he with his feet nailed faſt, looking for thee, with his armes ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to receiue thee, and with his head bowing downe to giue thee, as to another prodigal ſon, new kiſſes of peace, &amp; attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: from thence he calleth
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:180713:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>thee (if thou couldeſt here him) with many callings and cries, hearken therefore (ô my Chriſtian brother) and conſider this well with thy ſelfe, that if his prayer bee not heard, that hearkneth not vnto the cries of the poore, how much leſſe ſhall he bee heard that maketh him ſelf deaffe to ſuch cries as theſe are. Wherfore now determine with thy ſelfe to hearken vnto theſe cries, &amp; be fully reſolued to change thy ſinfull life, &amp; to liue a new life, and ſo ſhalt thou at the laſt poſſeſſe the ioyes which neuer ſhall end.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:87"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of John Oxenbridge (depiction of bull standing on bridge)</figDesc>
                  <q>CONSTANTIA ET LABORE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180713:87"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
